<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Impar conatui, or, Mr. J.B. the author of an answer to the animadversions on the Dean of St. Paul's vindication of the Trinity rebuk'd and prov'd to be wholly unfit for the great work he hath undertaken : with some account of the late scandalous animadversions on Mr. Hill's book intituled A vindication of the primitive fathers ... : in a letter to the Reverend Mr. R.E. / by Thomas Holdsworth.</title>
            <author>Holdsworth, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44140</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2407</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27413</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09838839</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09838839</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44236</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44140)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44236)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1360:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Impar conatui, or, Mr. J.B. the author of an answer to the animadversions on the Dean of St. Paul's vindication of the Trinity rebuk'd and prov'd to be wholly unfit for the great work he hath undertaken : with some account of the late scandalous animadversions on Mr. Hill's book intituled A vindication of the primitive fathers ... : in a letter to the Reverend Mr. R.E. / by Thomas Holdsworth.</title>
                  <author>Holdsworth, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Keblewhite,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bingham, Joseph, 1668-1723.</term>
               <term>Hill, Samuel, 1648-1716. --  Vindication of the primitive fathers against the imputations of Gilbert Lord Bishop of Sarum.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44236:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44236:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>IMPAR CONATUI:</hi> OR, Mr. <hi>J.B.</hi> the Author of an ANSWER TO THE ANIMADVERSIONS ON THE Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Vindication of the TRINITY, <hi>Rebuk'd</hi> and <hi>Prov'd</hi> TO BE WHOLLY <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfit</hi> for the <hi>Great Work</hi> he hath Undertaken. WITH Some Account of the Late <hi>Scandalous Animadverſions</hi> on Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s BOOK, Intituled, <hi>A Vindication of the Primitive Fathers againſt the Imputations of</hi> Gilbert <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> Sarum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a Letter to the Reverend Mr.</hi> R. E.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS HOLDSWORTH,</hi> M.A. Rector of <hi>North-Stoneham</hi> near <hi>Southampton.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quare deſine jam tibi videri,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quod ſoli tibi, Caecili, videris;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui Galbam ſalibus tuis, &amp; ipſum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Poſſis vincere Seſtium Caballum.</hi>
               </l>
               <bibl>M. Val. Mart. Epig. Lib. 1. Ep. 36.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Keblewhite,</hi> at the <hi>Swan</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard,</hi> MDCXCV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:44236:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44236:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>UPon the Peruſal of the following Papers ſent to me into the Country to note the Errata of the Preſs (which are many and bad) I found one or two of my own. The firſt is in the laſt Line but two of <hi>p. 5.</hi> where I ſpeak of an Enthymen as a Syllogiſm with two Terms and no more: Which Miſtake I was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warily betray'd into, by conſidering too ſlightly, and inferring too raſhly, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe an Enthymem is always under the Defect of a Major or a Minor Propoſition, therefore it wanted a Major or a Minor Term, and conſequently had but two Terms. But this the Reader (if he pleaſe to be ſo candid to me) may impute to that Inad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertency and want of critical Care, which is uſual enough in a private Letter to a
<pb facs="tcp:44236:3"/>Friend, as this was only deſign'd when this Miſtake eſcap'd me; or he may par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don it to a Country Retirement from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, and to a Deſuetude of the ſyllogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Practice for more than twenty Years. The ſecond (or rather what may ſeem to be ſo without a Caution) is in <hi>p. 27.</hi> at the Bottom of which I ſay, <hi>that Mr.</hi> J. B. <hi>will not find ſo much as one honeſt Man, that will tell him, that the Father here [viz. 1</hi> Cor. <hi>8.6.] is taken, as he takes the Word before, hypoſtatically, for the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> In which Words, I am ſenſible, I expreſs my ſelf ſomewhat too generally and looſely. And therefore I think fit to <hi>declare</hi> here (to prevent Cavil if I can) that I know well that many honeſt, Learned Men do take the Word [Father] here, hypoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, as 'tis oppos'd to and diſtinguiſh'd from the Second Perſon of the Bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity <hi>[the one Lord Jeſus Chriſt]</hi> in the End of the Verſe: But, as Mr. <hi>J.B.</hi> urges
<pb facs="tcp:44236:3"/>it <hi>Pref. p. 10.</hi> as the Word [Father] re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to the Words immediately precedent <hi>[to us]</hi> and to the Words immediately ſubſequent <hi>[of whom are All things]</hi> in this Senſe it is (as the Word [Father] in the Text ſtands thus related) that I deſire what I ſay in <hi>p. 27.</hi> may be underſtood: And in this Senſe I thought it to be plain and certain, that it is to be taken eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally: But if not, this I am very ſure of, that Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi>'s Argument, which I there un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, is never a whit the better for't. Many other Miſtakes, I am not ſecure but the Learned and Judicious Reader or Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> may find me guilty of: Of none, I hope, that are dangerous or ſcandalous, or in the leaſt prejudicial to the Holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Faith, or to my Holy Mother the Church of <hi>England.</hi> But whatever they may be, I reſolve, by the Grace of God, (as ſoon as ever I ſhall be convinced of them) to make what Amends and Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction I can, by owning my Offence, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:44236:4"/>by Silence or by a publick Retracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the Nature of it ſhall require. And I hope Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> (if he cannot fairly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer and clear himſelf from what I have objected againſt him) inſtead of ingaging himſelf any further in this ſublime Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy (for the Management of which I think I have prov'd him to be, <hi>what, God knows, I think my ſelf to be, <hi>Very Vnfit</hi>)</hi> will be ſo ingenuous, and have ſuch a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Regard for the Honour of our Holy Church and Religion (if he be really for it) as to do ſo too.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>THE Reader is deſired to take Notice of, and correct the following Errata; ſome of which quite alter the Senſe, and ſome diſturb it. Page 5 line 18 for <hi>Rarety</hi> r. <hi>Rarity,</hi> and l. 29 read thus, <hi>Syllogiſmus Truncatus? Triangulum Truncatum, I,</hi> &amp;c. p. 9 l. 21, 22. r. <hi>J. B.</hi> p. 10 l. 3 f. <hi>pert</hi> r. <hi>great,</hi> and l. 24 f. <hi>in</hi> r. <hi>is.</hi> p. 13 l. 22 f. <hi>other</hi> r. <hi>their.</hi> p. 19 l. 25 f. <hi>qui</hi> r. <hi>quae.</hi> p. 21 l. 11 f. <hi>Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> r. <hi>Adorable.</hi> p. 22 l. 20 f.
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> r.
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 25 l. 26 dele <hi>is</hi> before <hi>to.</hi> p. 28 l. 16 f. <hi>vice</hi> r. <hi>voce.</hi> p. 29 l. 26 after <hi>Adverſary,</hi> add <hi>doth not.</hi> p. 31 l. 16 r. <hi>of a.</hi> p. 33 l. 16 f. <hi>'tis</hi> r. <hi>is,</hi> and l. 22 f. <hi>on</hi> r. <hi>in.</hi> p. 40 l. 14 f. <hi>illo</hi> r. <hi>ille.</hi> p. 44 l. 15 r. <hi>Sole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm.</hi> p. 49 l. 14 dele [<hi>or</hi>] before [<hi>that</hi>] p. 52 l. 18 r. <hi>tells us,</hi> and l. 28 r. <hi>Father's being.</hi> p. 60 l. 5 f. <hi>quam</hi> r. <hi>quum.</hi> p. 72 l. 27 r. <hi>a vaſt.</hi> Several Miſpointings there are which are left to the Judgment of the Reader.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44236:4"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Intended you theſe Papers, according to my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, much ſooner. But beſides the Indiſpoſition I was under to write laſt Week (brought upon me, I fear, by our willful Journying almoſt all Night from a good Houſe and the beſt Company) the Anſwer of Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> A. M. to the Animadverſions on the Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Vindication of the Trinity, is to me ſuch a woful Example of <hi>Haſty Births,</hi> that you will pardon me, I hope, if the Fear of Abortion, of ſuch a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, ſcandalous Miſcarriage as Mr. <hi>J B</hi>'s whole Book is, hath made me go a Fortnight beyond my Reckoning.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> begins His Preface to the Reader with a very true and congruous Obſervation, That <hi>Haſty Births commonly are imperfect:</hi> And never, I think, was it more truly and fully Exemplify'd than by His own Deform'd Creature, this His Embryo of a Book. And whether He be in earneſt or no, when He ſays, That He <hi>hath reaſon to fear the Imperfections of it,</hi> I nothing doubt, but Time and the Animadverter (if He doth not think ſo Sorry an Author too much beneath Him, <q>
                  <hi>Scilicet à magnis ad T E deſcendere Tauris</hi>)</q> will quickly make it appear, That He hath much more Reaſon for ſuch a Fear than He is aware of.</p>
            <p>As a Prelibation of what I dare promiſe you'll have a full Draught hereafter, I ſhall, as I promiſed you, Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine this Doughty Champion's Preface, not the former
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44236:5"/>Part of it, in which He flouriſhes with an Account of the rare Exploits and mighty Atchievements of His Book (for that will belong to the Examiner of His Book) but the latter Part of it, in which, as Joab <hi>did</hi> Amaſa,
<note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 10.</note> 
               <hi>He takes the Animadverter by the Beard, and ſmites Him in the fifth Rib,</hi> and cracks and bounces, as if with His keen Ironies and blunt Charges, and blunter Arguments, <hi>He had kill'd Him dead, as if neither He nor any Body elſe ſhould ever have any more Occaſion to ſtrike Him again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For He proves Him, <hi>Pref. p.</hi> 8. <hi>to be blind paſt all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, blinder than the Dean's Son at the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, the meaneſt Sophiſter of a Year's ſtanding</hi> (which by the way, as He hath expreſs'd Himſelf, is a Complement upon the Dean's Son; for which the Dean and His Son cannot but think Themſelves much oblig'd to Him) <hi>that He wants to be taught the firſt Rudiments of Logick: That He is a Perſon of no Logick at all: That 'tis plain He doth not yet know the Predicate and Subject of a Propoſition,</hi> p. 9. <hi>That in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity He is not only guilty of Error, but downright Blaſphemy, ſuch blaſphemous Stuff,</hi> that the modeſt good Man <hi>cannot relate it without Bluſhing,</hi> p. 10. and this Blaſphemy is the Conſequence of <hi>His great Ignorance of the receiv'd Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Church,</hi> p. 12. <hi>that He is ſo ignorant, as if He had never read the Scriptures, never learn'd His Catechiſm, nay not his Creed,</hi> p. 10. Poor Animadverter!</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Omnibus Invideas, Livide, Nemo Tibi.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Now, Sir, I cannot deny but that the Animadverter hath been much Declaim'd againſt as an Envious, Proud, Ill-natur'd, Scurrilous Perſon; and I muſt needs ſay, if he had not been too much ſo, He could not have treated ſo great and good a Man, and of ſuch excellent Parts (as the Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s certainly is, and is generally and juſtly allow'd to be) with ſo much Scorn and Contempt,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44236:5"/>ſo rudely and unchriſtianly. But I am ſure you will agree with me, That as bad as the Animadverter is or can be repreſented to be, by His greateſt Enemies, it was never heard before, that He was ſo incomparably Ignorant, ſuch an egregious Blockhead as this Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> attempts to prove Him: But on the contrary was always, when in the Univerſity and ſince, allow'd to be a Man of great Wit and Parts, and a well Educated and well Studied Scholar.</p>
            <p>And therefore, Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> in Treating and Repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Animadverter at this boiſterous Rate, doth either juſtify the Animadverter in His Uſage of the Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, or doth expoſe and condemn Himſelf for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as Bad and as Impudent at leaſt as He paints the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverter: And doth by it reduce Himſelf to another unlucky Dilemma, That either all others are Fools and miſtaken in their Notions of the Animadverter, or He Himſelf is ſo in His Character of Him: Such a Character as was never before given Him, and with Truth and Conſcience never can: A Character that reflects rudely and undutifully upon the Univerſity and upon the Church, and (which, I doubt, He was not well aware of) moſt ſeverely upon Himſelf. For by this Character which He ſo weakly and vainly endeavours to prove and fix upon the Animadverter, He ſtrongly proves and effectually diſcovers, that 'tis He Himſelf is the Man to whom in good earneſt, and with too much Truth it belongs.</p>
            <p>That this is ſo, I think, I ſhall be able to make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to you very plainly and fully, by Attacking this Gentleman in His ſtrongeſt Works, in the Five or Six laſt Pages of His Preface; in which He takes all the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages againſt the Animadverter that poſſibly He can, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles out Two or Three Paſſages out of His whole Book of <hi>Tritheiſm Charg'd,</hi> &amp;c. which He thinks to be the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt indefenſible; and then plays upon Him, with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44236:6"/>all His Might, His whole Artillery. And here, one would think, if ever, He ſhould do the Animadverter's Buſineſs, as He thinks He has done: But that now ſhall be try'd.</p>
            <p>Three things He ſets upon the Animadverter for. The Firſt is produc'd as <hi>an Inſtance of the Animadverter's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Judgment in the Science,</hi> as He calls it, <hi>of Logick;</hi> after which, He ſays, <hi>He will conclude his Epiſtle,</hi> Pref. <hi>p.</hi> 7. Though after this, before He concludes, He produces Two diſtinct Inſtances more, to convict Him of Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, Heterodoxy and Blaſphemy in Divinity, and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid Ignorance in Logic: Which Two diſtinct Inſtances too He calls but One, <hi>Pref. p.</hi> 10. from whence, I doubt not, if He had made ſuch a Diſcovery in the Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, He would preſently have cried out and Inferr'd for certain, that this ignorant Animadverter could not tell Twenty; that the Animadverter was ſo very ignorant, that He knew not that Two and One made Three, or that One added to One made Two. But I am not willing (and have no need) to make ſuch Inferences: and I wiſh they were leſs frequent in Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>As for the Animadverter's <hi>Profound Judgment,</hi> by which this Catechreſtical Man means His Profound Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, <hi>in the Science,</hi> forſooth, <hi>of Logick,</hi> That is plain to a Demonſtration, as plain, as that there cannot be a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle with Two Sides only, or a Square with Three.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For</hi> ſays Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> very wittily and ſhrewdly, <hi>A Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſm with two Terms and no more, is a Triangle with two Sides only, or a Square with three. Bleſs me! thought I,</hi> what doth this Man mean? The leaſt he can mean is, That a Syllogiſm with two Terms and no more, is as abſurd and impoſſible, as a Triangle with two Sides only, or a Square with three. If ſo, then here's a Mathematical Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration for you, Sir, That this naughty, ignorant Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverter doth the Reverend Dean much Wrong. For how can the Reverend Dean make a Syllogiſm with two
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44236:6"/>Terms and no more, when the thing is as impoſſible as a Triangle with two Sides only, or a Square with three? For a Syllogiſm with two Terms and no more ('tis no better nor worſe) is a Triangle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon my Word, Sir, this is a notable cunning Way to clear the Dean, and becoming the Acumen of Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> very well.</p>
            <p>But what now, If a Syllogiſm with two Terms and no more, be not a Triangle with two Sides only, or a Square with three; but do as vaſtly differ, as that which is not only poſſible but very eaſie, uſual and common, differs from that which is utterly impoſſible? What then? why then 'tis one Demonſtration, that Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> is not the Man ſome Folks may take Him to be.</p>
            <p>If you know, Sir, how to direct to this Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> (for I do not) let me beg the Favour of you to write to Him, that your Friend <hi>T. H.</hi> if he hath any Occaſion for ſuch a Rarety as He thought was impoſſible to be had for Love or Money, hath a Thouſand Syllogiſms at His Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and each Syllogiſm (you may pawn your Honour for Him if you pleaſe) ſhall have but two Terms and no more (and I queſtion not but the Reverend Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s hath ſo many more at His Service) and all that He expects in Return, is, That Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> if poſſibly He can, would be ſo kind to Him as to oblige Him but with one Poor Triangle with two Sides only, or a Square with three, which He pleaſes, or can beſt afford.</p>
            <p>Did this learned Logician never hear of ſuch a thing as <hi>Syllogiſmus Truncatus, Triangulum Truncatum?</hi> I am ſure He never did. Can this <hi>J. B.</hi> be A. M. and never hear of a Syllogiſm call'd an Enthymem? Or not know that an Enthymem is a Syllogiſm with two Terms and no more? And is an Enthymem therefore a Triangle with two Sides only?</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:44236:7"/>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> you'll ſay, means a Syllogiſm of three Propoſitions, ſuch as the Dean's is; and that 'tis as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for ſuch a Syllogiſm to have but two Terms and no more, as it is for a Triangle to have but two Sides: Why then is Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> ſo very impertinent, as to take up a Page or two, to prove that which is impoſſible to be otherwiſe?</p>
            <p>But if it be as impoſſible for a Syllogiſm of three Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions to have but two Terms, as it is for a Triangle to have but two Sides only; what will Mr. <hi>J.B.</hi> ſay of a Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſm of three Propoſitions, and but of one Term only? And yet ſuch a Syllogiſm, to the beſt of my Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance (for I have not the Book by me) He may find in the Firſt Volume of the late A. B. <hi>Tillotſon</hi>'s Sermons in the Preface againſt <hi>J. S.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>If a Rule be a Rule, then a Rule is a Rule; but a Rule is a Rule,</hi> ergo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>A Syllogiſm indeed of three Propoſitions with two Terms and no more, is a very naughty, vicious Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſm; but if it will therefore follow, that 'tis a Triangle with two Sides only, I'll undertake to prove, when you pleaſe, that Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> Himſelf is a Triangle with two Sides only. For why will it not as well follow, that a naughty, vicious Diſputant (the worſt that ever Water wet) as Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> is, is, for being ſo, a Triangle with two Sides only, as that a naughty, vicious Syllogiſm is ſo? The worſt that can be ſaid of a Syllogiſm with two Terms and no more, is, that it is a very bad, falſe Syllogiſm; but yet a Syllogiſm ſtill it is, as much as <hi>J. B.</hi> is a Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, as falſe and as bad as he is; and it implies, I'll ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie it no more a Contradiction (as a Triangle with two Sides only certainly doth) to ſay that a Syllogiſm is with two Terms only, than to ſay, that Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> is a Diſputant.</p>
            <p>In a Word, If we will take Mr. <hi>J. B</hi>'s ignorant, foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Fancy (for ſuch it is) in a more candid Senſe than it will well bear; if, that is, it ſhould be granted that by a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44236:7"/>Syllogiſm's being a Triangle with two Sides only, He means no more by it, than that it is a faulty, vicious Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſm, then let the Reverend Dean look to Himſelf; for if to be a faulty, vicious Syllogiſm is to be a Triangle with two ſides only, then ſuch a Triangle hath Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> made the Reverend Dean's Syllogiſm to be. For whether the Animadverter can make good, what he ſays, that His Syllogiſm hath two Terms and no more or no, that I will not meddle with: Let the Animadverter look to 't. But this, I think, I may be very ſure of, that His bleſſed De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender hath defended it into a Syllogiſm utterly indefenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by any of the allow'd Rules of Logick: And this, I doubt not, I ſhall prove to you to your Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>This is the Dean's Syllogiſm. <q>Three diſtinct infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite intelligent Perſons are three Gods: But there are not three diſtinct Gods: And therefore, there are not three diſtinct infinite intelligent Perſons in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</q>
            </p>
            <p>After the Repetition of which Syllogiſm, thus begins the Puiſſant <hi>J. B. The Major of this Propoſition is falſe. Bleſs me! though I,</hi> will this Man deny the Four and Twenty Letters? Did you ever, Sir, in all your days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, hear the Major of a Propoſition denied? How might I expoſtulate with this great Logician in His own Words, in the laſt Paragraph of this Page? <hi>I turn'd over with great ſpeed to</hi> the Errata, thinking I might find another Word <hi>for Propoſition,</hi> but finding none, I will hope in Charity that 'tis the Fault of the Preſs; and that 'tis <hi>the Major of this Syllogiſm,</hi> which He would ſay <hi>is falſe: But what other Fault to find with it,</hi> that He declares, <hi>was paſt His Skill in Logick. Alas! who can help</hi> J. B.<hi>'s Blindneſs? The Reverend Dean's Son at the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> though He ſhould be <hi>the meaneſt Sophiſter of a Year's ſtanding</hi> (which I hope He is not, unleſs He hath the ill Luck to have ſuch an A. M. as <hi>J. B.</hi> for His Tutor) <hi>could have told this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44236:8"/>Logician and Philoſopher,</hi> that as He has manag'd <hi>this innocent Syllogiſm</hi> (as He calls it) beſides that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor Propoſition is falſe, it is ſo far from being a good Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſm and having no other Fault, that it is utterly falſe and indefenſible, as a Syllogiſm, by any of the allow'd Rules in Logick: And that though <hi>He is aſhamed</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth! (as He fondly ſays He is) to <hi>ſpend His Reader's Time and abuſe His Patience, to teach this great Dictator in Philoſophy and Divinity</hi> [the Animadverter] <hi>the Firſt Rudiments of Logick;</hi> yet 'tis He Himſelf is ſuch an arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant ſilly Dictator as wants to be taught the Firſt Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Logick, if ever any Simpleton of a Dictator did. For there is not a Freſhman in the Univerſity of but a quarter of a Year's ſtanding, if any due Care has been taken of Him, but can tell this huffing <hi>Thraſo,</hi> that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Major, Minor and Middle-Term, which is but the remote Matter of a Syllogiſm, every Categorical Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſm muſt have its Form, which conſiſts in Mood and Figure; and if it be not of ſuch or ſuch a Figure, which is a due, regular Diſpoſal of the Middle-Term with the two Extreams, which are the Parts of the Queſtion, the Freſhman will tell Him (and both the Univerſities will juſtifie Him in it) that the Syllogiſm cannot be without Fault (whether <hi>J. B.</hi> ſees it or no) but muſt be vicious.</p>
            <p>Let us ſee now how this glorious Defender of the Dean will diſpoſe of this Middle-Term which He has found out: For there's a pretty Inſtrument in Logick, you know, call'd <hi>Pons Aſinorum,</hi> which may help a poor Man, upon Occaſion, to the Middle-Term, but the Craft is in diſpoſing it aright; or elſe He will never make a good Syllogiſm but by Chance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is clear,</hi> ſays our Champion, <hi>[Three diſtinct Gods] is the Middle-Term as not entring the Concluſion.</hi> Well, and what then? Why then, having made this notable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, the next thing to be done, is to ſecure a Major
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44236:8"/>and a Minor: And to that end, by the Help of honeſt <hi>Dutrieu</hi> (a little Book that a Man may almoſt venture to ſwear he never read, or underſtood, or hath forgot) <hi>the Verb Subſtantive</hi> eſt <hi>or</hi> ſunt <hi>in Latin</hi> [to diſtinguiſh it, I ſuppoſe from the Verb Subſtantive <hi>eſt</hi> or <hi>ſunt</hi> in Greek or Hebrew, or ſome other Tongue in which the Verb Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive <hi>eſt</hi> or <hi>ſunt</hi> may not be ſo ſerv'd] <hi>is in theſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Reſolvendum hoc modo, eſt exiſtens, ſunt exiſtentes;</hi> ſo ſays <hi>Dutrieu, Logica,</hi> p. 3.</p>
            <p>What Pity it is, That a Man who ſeems to have read no farther in Logick than to the third Page in <hi>Dutrieu,</hi> ſhould be ſo ill-advis'd, as to be ſhewing his Skill in Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick againſt the Learned Animadverter. For if he had read any farther, or any other Logick, he could not well be ignorant, that there's no Neceſſity at all of thus <hi>Reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Concluſion of the Dean's Syllogiſm</hi> to make a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor and a Minor. It had as much a Major and a Minor before it was thus reſolv'd, as ſince; and, to uſe His own Words, <hi>None but a Perſon of no Logick could be ignorant of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>J. B</hi>'s <hi>eſt,</hi> is as much a Propoſition, and hath as much a Subject and a Predicate, as Mr. <hi>J. B</hi>'s <hi>eſt talis qualis.</hi> For <hi>eſt ſecundi adjecti</hi> is altogether as ſufficient for a Propoſition, as when it is the mere verbal <hi>Copula,</hi> or <hi>eſt tertii adjecti;</hi> nay, it makes the Propoſition more large and comprehenſive, that is, more Affirmative and Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: And therefore nothing but groſs Ignorance, which as the wiſe Man ſays,
<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 14.16.</note> maketh a certain ſort of Creature to rage and be confident; nothing but this could have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd this fooliſh Man to inſult the Animadverter, as he doth here in his laſt Paragraph, <hi>p.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>The Animadverter, no doubt, knows ſtill, what he did, I believe, Forty Years ago, that there may be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition Affirmative or Negative with <hi>eſt ſecundi adjecti,</hi> as well as with <hi>eſt tertii;</hi> and that He hath no Occaſion at
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44236:9"/>all for <hi>eſt tertii adjecti,</hi> to prevent the Dean's Concluſion from being <hi>a Marriage of a Man to himſelf.</hi> Every ſimple Chriſtian, without <hi>J. B</hi>'s pert Learning, knows that two are enough to make a Match, if they can be married, and are not within the prohibited Degrees: And therefore he had no Occaſion at all to go to Father <hi>Dutrieu,</hi> to give [Are not Exiſtent] to be married to [three diſtinct, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] In Reverence I forbear to ſpeak it out.</p>
            <p>But when all is done, let him do what he can for his Life, he can never make a Marriage of it. For the Dean's Concluſion, being a Negative Propoſition, is rather a Divorce than a Marriage: So <hi>Petrus à ſancto Joſeph</hi> will tell Him [in <hi>Log. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.] <hi>In Propoſitionibus Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivis Verbum medium non ſatis propriè videtur dici Copula, cum non uniat inter ſe extrema, ſed potius illa ſeparet.</hi> So unlucky is this Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> in his parabolical Wit.
<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 26.7.</note> 
               <hi>The Legs of the Lame are not equal:</hi> So—</p>
            <p>Well, but now Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> (his Modeſty notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) hath taught the Animadverter <hi>his Firſt Rudiments in Logick,</hi> and told him how <hi>the Verb Subſtantive</hi> eſt <hi>or</hi> ſunt <hi>in Latin is to be reſolv'd, and that the Concluſion of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Dean's Syllogiſm is reſolv'd into this,</hi> viz. <hi>and therefore three diſtinct, infinite, intelligent Perſons in the Godhead are not exiſting; and that the Term exiſting in the third Term in this Syllogiſm, and to be ſupplied in this Syllogiſm both in the Minor Propoſition and Concluſion, and that none but a Perſon of no Logick could have been ignorant of it;</hi> now then, after this ſharp Reprimand and Lecture, the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverter is to take the Dean's Syllogiſm in its Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, according to the Second Edition of it, by Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> Thus;</p>
            <p>Three diſtinct, infinite, intelligent Perſons are three Gods:</p>
            <p>But three diſtinct Gods are not exiſting:</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:44236:9"/>
            <p>And therefore three diſtinct, infinite, intelligent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are not exiſting.</p>
            <p>Now I deſire to know what Figure this Syllogiſm is of? It cannot be of the Firſt: For then [three diſtinct Gods] which is allow'd to be the Middle Term, muſt be the Subject in the Major Propoſition and the Predicate in the Minor. It cannot be of the Second, for then the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Term muſt be the Predicate of the Minor as well as of the Major. It cannot be of the Third, for then the Middle Term muſt be the Subject both of Major and Minor. And therefore I know no Remedy for him, if he will have his Syllogiſm of any Figure at all, but to go to Old <hi>Galen,</hi> and to give him his Fee for a Fourth: And if according to that, he can juſtifie that the Major Term may be the Subject of the Concluſion, as he hath made it in his Syllogiſm, it may be worth his Money, for what I know. But if the <hi>Major Terminus</hi> be in all Syllogiſms of the Fourth Figure, according to any of the Five Moods belonging to it, always the Predicate of the Concluſion, then neither can <hi>Galen,</hi> nothing can help him.</p>
            <p>In every Syllogiſm of the Fourth Figure, the Minor Term is predicated of the Middle Term, and the Middle Term of the Major; ſo that the ſame Middle Term is a Major to the Major, and yet a Minor to the Minor, and ſo the Minor Term is made a Major to the Major; and yet becauſe the Major Term is always in the Concluſion pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated of the Minor Term, it is a Major to the Minor, which, as <hi>Scheibler</hi> hath obſerv'd
<note n="*" place="margin">Op. Log. de Syl. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>Art.</hi> 2.</note>, is as abſurd, as if we ſhould ſay, ſome Man is greater than <hi>Goliah</hi> and yet leſs than <hi>David:</hi> And therefore, ſaith he, <hi>Nunquam au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus naturaliter diſſerentes, tales quartae Figurae Syllogiſmos formare;</hi> and the Fourth Figure by Logicians is generally Reprobated.
<note n="‖" place="margin">Vid. Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roem 1. prior. <hi>c.</hi> 8. in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. &amp; Zabar. in <hi>lib.</hi> de 4 Fig. Syllog. &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terp. ad 1. prior.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:44236:10"/>
            <p>But allowing it to be no Fault nor Diſcredit to a Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſm to be of the Fourth Figure, yet to make the Minor Term, as he hath done, the Predicate of the Concluſion and the Major the Subject, is to make the Minor the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor, and the Major the Minor; and this is ſuch a Fault and Diſcredit to Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> and his Syllogiſm, as will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them to the Cenſure and Contempt of every Baby in Logick, and ſuch as I never expect to ſee clear'd.</p>
            <p>Having thus conſider'd Mr. <hi>J. B</hi>'s Syllogiſm for the Dean, let us next conſider the Animadverter's for the Dean; and we ſhall eaſily ſee, which, in this Matter, is the Dean's beſt-Friend, and hath done him the beſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> or the Animadverter.</p>
            <p>The Animadverter <hi>ſets it right for Him,</hi> Thus;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Three diſtinct, infinite, intelligent Perſons are three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Gods; But Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt are not three diſtinct Gods; and therefore Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt are not three infinite, intelligent Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this is unqueſtionably a good Syllogiſm of the Second Figure, and is as much to the Dean's Purpoſe, as he can deſire. But as plainly good as the Animadverter's Syllogiſm for the Dean and the Socinian is, and ſuch as can be prov'd by Mood and Figure; yet Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> to ſhew his Skill in Logick, is ſo hardy as to undertake to prove from it, to <hi>make it plain, that the Animadverter does not yet know the Subject and Predicate of a Propoſition.</hi> Really, Sir, I muſt profeſs to you, that I think I never before met with any thing ſo very confident and ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ignorant in the Art of Reaſoning as this Man is.</p>
            <p>Here is a Firſt and a Second (I cannot call 'em Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, I know not what to call 'em bad enough) advanc'd againſt the Syllogiſm as ſupply'd and perfected by the Animadverter.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>The Animadverter,</hi> he ſays, <hi>has chang'd the whole Syllogiſm.</hi> Chang'd it indeed he has, and the Dean,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44236:10"/>if he pleaſes, may thank him for't: For he has, like a Man of Art, ſet it right for him, as he pretended: he has chang'd it from bad to good; from being infirm and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Exception, into a very ſound, robuſt Conſtitution, ſuch as cannot be ſhaken and expos'd. And what Harm, I pray, is there in all this? Ay! But the Animadverter has chang'd <hi>the whole</hi> Syllogiſm. Pray, Sir, look a little upon his Book and obſerve how he proves this, and you'll find that his whole Proof amounts to this and no more, <hi>viz.</hi> The Animadverter has chang'd the Concluſion of the Syllogiſm, <hi>ergo</hi> he has chang'd the whole Syllogiſm. But how has the Animadverter chang'd the Concluſion of the Dean's Syllogiſm? 'Tis certain, Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> hath chang'd it with a Witneſs, and moſt abſurdly, contrary to all Rules of Logick, hath made the Predicate of the Dean's Concluſion to be the Subject. But 'tis plain the Predicate, as it ſtands in the Dean's Concluſion and in the Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verter's is the ſame; and I am ſomewhat inclin'd to think, that ſo is the Subject too, only in one 'tis under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and in the other 'tis expreſs'd: And if Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> and I were to wait on the Dean together to ask him, what Perſons he means, and what be other Names whom he denies in His Concluſion to be three diſtinct, infinite, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Perſons: Do you not think, Sir, or rather are you not ſure, that the Dean would be on my Side, and anſwer, That he means Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt? And then how would Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> ſlouch? Then, I hope, the Animadverter hath not chang'd the Concluſion at all, but only made it more expreſs.</p>
            <p>Did ever this <hi>J. B.</hi> hear of any other diſtinct, infinite, intelligent Perſons, (which the Orthodox aſſert and the Socinians deny) than Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt? And is it not then a very judicious, wiſe Remark and Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the Dean in his Concluſion, <hi>univerſally denies that there are any diſtinct, infinite, intelligent Perſons in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44236:11"/>the Godhead;</hi> and that the Animadverter in his Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>only particularly denies that Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt are diſtinct, infinite, intelligent Perſons?</hi> Certainly, nothing in the World can be more abſurd and ridiculous than this whole Paragraph, except it be his next which follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Then to prove [<hi>to make it plain,</hi> very <hi>plain] that this profound Logician</hi> [the Animadverter] <hi>who ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten upbraids others with the want of Logick, does not yet know the Subject and Predicate of a Propoſition, and that this great Critick</hi> (which one would hardly believe almoſt) though he was a long while the Celebrated Oratour for the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> yet, is ſuch a monſtrous Blockhead, that he cannot conſtrue a Sentence of the plaineſt Latin, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Care be taken by Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> to put the Words for him in their natural Order: Por though <hi>the Subject commonly precedes the Verb or Copula, and the Predicate commonly follows,</hi> yet Learned, Able Mr. <hi>J. B. craves leave to tell this great Critick</hi> [the Animadverter] <hi>that the Rule is not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal; and Mr.</hi> J. B. <hi>finds</hi> (for 'tis very plain) <hi>that the Animadverter</hi> never could tell, or <hi>cannot yet tell, when it fails.</hi> So that if the Predicate of a Propoſition happens to ſtand before the Verb <hi>eſt,</hi> and the Subject to follow, the Animadverter is clearly gone; he cannot tell which is the Nominative Caſe that is to come before the Verb <hi>eſt,</hi> and which is to follow; that is, he cannot tell which is the Subject and which is the Predicate. Little did I think that this Animadverter had been ſuch an arrant Dunce!</p>
            <p>Now, I ſay, to prove all this, is as eaſie a thing with Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> as 'tis for him to confute St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> and to make Fools of all the Schoolmen and Moderns.</p>
            <p>Thus then he proves it; to which I beg you to attend a little, that you may ſee what a ſpecial A. M. this <hi>J. B.</hi> is, and how fit he is to engage in ſuch a Controverſy as he has undertaken.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:44236:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Concluſion,</hi> ſays he, <hi>of the laſt Syllogiſm</hi> (by which he means, and, in the next Line but one after, calls, the former Syllogiſm; which, by the way, every Man living of common Senſe, muſt needs ſee to be Nonſenſe and a Contradiction) <hi>not the Subject but the Predicate was to be ſupplied: Three infinite,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Perſons in the former Syllogiſm</hi> (which, as I obſerv'd, he juſt before calls the laſt Syllogiſm) <hi>was the Subject and not Predicate of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion: Whereas in the Animadverter's Syllogiſm, he has made three infinite Perſons the Predicate;</hi> that is (and I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to your ſelf and to all the World, whether I do not expound him fairly) becauſe Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> according to his excellent, unuſual Skill in the <hi>Science</hi> of Logick, has made the <hi>Major Terminus</hi> [three diſtinct, infinite, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] of the Dean's Syllogiſm, to be the Subject of the Concluſion, which according to all the allow'd Rules of Logick ought to be the Predicate; and the Middle Term, being the Predicate of the Major, has made the Minor Term the Predicate both of the Minor Propoſition and the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and by ſo doing, has blindly expoſed his Syllogiſm as a defenceleſs, deform'd thing, to be ridicul'd and baffl'd by every little Sophiſter and Freſhman of the Univerſities, and hath given full Proof to the World of his moſt ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous, contemptible Ignorance in that which he ſo much pretends to: Whereas the Animadverter, in his Syllogiſm, has plac'd the Predicate exactly right, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the indiſputable Rules of Art, plac'd all the three Terms of his Syllogiſm in their due, legitimate Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, according to the Second Figure; from whence what doth Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> inferr? Certainly, what could never enter into the Head of any Man but an <hi>J. B. From whence,</hi> ſays Mr. <hi>J. B. 'tis plain</hi> (plain I dare ſwear not to any Man upon the Earth beſides himſelf) <hi>that this profound Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> [the Animadverter] <hi>who ſo often upbraids others with the want of Logick, Does not yet know the Subject and Predicate of a Propoſition,</hi> &amp;c. as before.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:44236:12"/>
            <p>And now, Sir, You cannot chuſe, I am ſure, but ſtand amaz'd at the Confidence and Ignorance of this <hi>Thraſo,</hi> to ſee him, upon this, clapping his Wings and crowing, as if there were no Remedy now for the Animadverter but to ſhoot the Pit, and to run and hide his Head, as a Man (he <hi>perſwades himſelf</hi> by the mighty Force of his full and clear Evidence againſt him) <hi>not eaſily to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten or pardoned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whether he hath more expos'd the Animadverter for <hi>His Syllogiſm with two Terms, and a Propoſition with one Term</hi> (of neither of which doth it appear that the Animadverter is guilty) or himſelf, for <hi>ſaying that a Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſm with two Terms and no more, is a Triangle with two Sides only, or a Square with three: For denying the Major of a Propoſition</hi> (if it be not the Fault of the Preſs, which his palpable Ignorance may make a Doubt:) <hi>For endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to help the Dean out by changing a Propoſition</hi> de Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Adjacente, <hi>into a Propoſition</hi> de Tertio Adjacente, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which, he ſeems to underſtand nothing at all of the Matter: For making that to be a Marriage of a Subject and Predicate, which is plainly a Divorce: For making a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate Syllogiſm for the Dean of the Fourth Figure with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion inverted: For making the very ſame Syllogiſm in the ſame Reſpect to be the laſt, and the former beyond all Poſſibility of evading the Contradiction:</hi> Whether, I ſay, Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> hath more expos'd the Animadverter for what he doth not appear to be guilty of; or himſelf in theſe things, and much more in the Compaſs of two or three Pages, of which, I think, I may venture to ſay, I have prov'd him guilty; and which of the two will be moſt <hi>eaſily forgotten and pardoned,</hi> the <hi>Inſulting</hi> Animadverter with <hi>a Bottom,</hi> or <hi>Inſuiting J. B.</hi> with <hi>no Bottom,</hi> I ſubmit, Sir, to your correct Judgment and impartial Determination.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:44236:12"/>
            <p n="2">2. The Second thing the Animadverter is taken to task for, is his Abſurdity, Heterodoxy, and Blaſphemy in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, together with his ſtupid Ignorance in Logick.</p>
            <p>And of this we have two peremptory Inſtances as clear as the Meridian Light.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is the Animadverter's <hi>Noting this for an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and illogical Propoſition, to ſay That God is the Father,</hi> Pref. <hi>p.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>The Second is <hi>his telling us that the Term [three intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Perſons,</hi> i. e. the three eternal, infinite, intelligent Perſons, of whom the Animadverter ſpeaks before, <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm,</hi> p. 130.] <hi>is adequately and convertibly predicated of [God.]</hi> Pref. <hi>p.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>To note this for an abſurd and illogical Propoſition, to ſay That God is the Father;</hi> what ſhall Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> call it? <hi>Shall he call it an Error in Divinity? It is too mild a Name, he cannot but eſteem it downright Blaſphemy; ſuch blaſphemous Stuff that his Modeſty cannot but bluſh to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this is ſo, he makes it very plain, if you pleaſe to obſerve him and can underſtand him, 1ſt. from Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, 2dly from Logick; and then up again he gets upon the Animadverter and treads upon him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> from Scripture. That's very full and decretory againſt the Animadverter. <hi>For how often do the ſacred Scriptures tell us, that God ſent his Son, gave his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son? Ergo,</hi> it is a very plain Caſe, God is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For <hi>he challenges the Animadverter any other ways to expound them than by the Term of the Father,</hi> viz. <hi>the Father ſent his Son, gave his only begotten Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No doubt the Animadverter will ſo expound them, and ſo expounded will <hi>bluſh,</hi> I believe, as much as Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> can, to ſay the Expreſſions are abſurd and illogical, and will bluſh again for the Univerſity and Church, if he hath any Tenderneſs for them, to ſee a Man who writes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:44236:13"/>himſelf A. M. and Presbyter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to pretend to diſpute in Print concerning the moſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult Point in the World; and yet, to write at ſuch a looſe, ridiculous, childiſh Rate.</p>
            <p>The Animadverter Denies that God is the Father, and Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> to confute him effectually from Scripture, and to convict him of Blaſphemy, proves from Scripture what 'tis certain he does not deny. All that he pretends to, for what I can ſee, from Scripture, is, That the Father may be put in Appoſition to God. <hi>Does not Scripture, all the Creeds,</hi> ſays he, <hi>uſe the Expreſſion of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> Yes! And who denies it? Doth not he think, in his Conſcience, that the Animadverter uſes it himſelf? Or doth he think that he never ſays his Creed or his Prayers? And can a Man in the moſt ſolemn Manner profeſs that he believes in God the Father; and upon his Knees, in the Litany, invoke God the Father. Can ſuch a Man be ſuppos'd, with any Candour and Charity, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Expreſſion unlawful, abſurd and illogical? his Adverſary therefore cannot be ſuppos'd (no, not by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) to deny the Paſſages which he urges out of Scripture, nor what he immediately and directly inferrs from them. To what purpoſe then doth this Man ask over and over, <hi>Are theſe Expreſſions abſurd and illogical?</hi> Unleſs it be to expoſe his Folly and Impertinence, and to ſhew that he loves, what no Man of Senſe elſe can, to hear himſelf talk.</p>
            <p>The Animadverter certainly, doth not deny that our Bleſſed Lord is the Son of God the Father, or that God the Father is as proper and orthodox an Expreſſion, as it is uſual: But he denies, That therefore it follows that 'tis proper and Logical to ſay, that God is the Father. But that, it ſeems, is plainly for Want of Logick in the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverter. <hi>For,</hi> ſays Mr. <hi>J. B. had the Animadverter that Skill in Logick, be ſo often upbraids others with the want of, he would have known that God the Father is equivalent in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:44236:13"/>Logick to this, that God is A Father, and if A Father THE Father.</hi> Very profound! I dare ſwear the Animadverter doth not underſtand Logick, as this Man does, nor any Body elſe that can be ſaid to underſtand it at all. In what Logick is it, that God the Father is equivalent to this, that God <hi>IS</hi> a Father? I am apt to think that this Man hath got a Logick of his own, which he keeps lock'd up for his own private Uſe upon Occaſion, and in that perhaps, it may be, but I dare ſay in no other. Is the Expreſſion, God the Father, a Propoſition? What then, to exclaim in his own Way, <hi>Can there be a Propoſition without a Copula? That is, in other Words, Can there be an Affirmative and nothing Affirm'd?</hi> If the Animadverter had ſaid any thing like this, what a Noiſe ſhould we have had about <hi>the Marriage of a Man to himſelf,</hi> and that without a Copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la too? If God the Father be equivalent in Logick to this, that God <hi>IS</hi> a Father; then, I hope, Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that God <hi>is</hi> a Father, is equivalent to God <hi>the</hi> Father; and if ſo, God the Father muſt be a Propoſition; there's no avoiding it: For therefore, a Propoſition is ſaid to be equipollent or equivalent, becauſe there's another Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to which it is equivalent: And hence it is ſet down by Logicians, as one of the firſt things requir'd to denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate a Propoſition equipollent or equivalent, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſint (non una, ſed) duae plureſve Propoſitiones, qui dicuntur aequipollen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</hi> And if God the Father be a Propoſition, then there muſt be a Subject and a Predicate, and then the Father is predicated of God, and that's impoſſible unleſs we will ſay God is the Father: And if the Expreſſion be come to that at laſt, then Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> is gone again, for then it will not be equivalent to this, that God is the Father, but iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical with it. For that is ſaid to be equivalent, and it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be otherwiſe, which hath the ſame Senſe but not the ſame Words: But that is ſaid to be identical, which hath the ſame Words as well as the ſame Sence.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:44236:14"/>
            <p>But not to inſiſt upon this, I will allow Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> if he pleaſes, That it may be inferr'd from this Expreſſion [God the Father] either that God is the Father, or that the Father is God; which is as much, as in reaſon he can deſire. But now how will Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> prove that 'tis the former Propoſition which muſt be inferr'd, and not the latter; or that both may be inferr'd? If it muſt follow from this Expreſſion [God the Father] that God <hi>IS</hi> the Father, that is, That the Father is properly and Logically predicated of God, then it muſt be upon this Ground; That whenever one Word is put truly in Appoſition to another Word (as here the Word Father is put in Appoſition to the Word God) that Word muſt be truly predicable of the Word to which it is put in Appoſition: But this is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly not ſo. For a Species may be, and very frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is, put in Appoſition to a Genus, and an individuum to a Species; yet, I hope, Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> will not ſay, That therefore the Species is to be predicated of the Genus, and the Individuum of the Species. In this Expreſſion, [a Living Creature Man] Man is put in Appoſition to a Living Creature, doth it therefore follow, that a Living Creature is a Man? This would be a very good way to prove a Man to be an Horſe. A Maſter of Arts and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Mr. <hi>J.B.</hi> where Mr. <hi>J.B.</hi> is put in Appoſition to a Maſter of Arts and Presbyter of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Doth it therefore follow, that this Propoſition [A Maſter of Arts and Presbyter of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi>] is no abſurd, illogical Propoſition? If not, ſome arch, malicious Sophiſter or other may prove me to be Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> which (whatever Mr. <hi>J. B</hi>'s Preferments may be) I would not be for Two-pence: Unleſs Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> by his mighty Skill in Logick, will prove himſelf not to be the Author of this Preface, and the following Book.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:44236:14"/>
            <p>A Thouſand Inſtances of this Nature may be given. But it may be ſufficient <hi>to tell this great Critick,</hi> That when one Word is put in Appoſition to another, it is ſometimes, as Grammarians tell us, <hi>Reſtringendae Generalitatis gratiâ,</hi> to Reſtrain and Limit the Signification of that Word to which it is put in Appoſition, as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbs Roma, Animal Equus:</hi> And for this Reaſon, I doubt not, you'll allow, for this very Reaſon is the Father in this Expreſſion which Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> urges, put in Appoſition to God, to reſtrain the Word God, which is common to all the Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the ever Bleſſed, moſt Admirable Trinity, to the Signification only of the Firſt Perſon; to ſignifie that God who ſent his Son, who gave his only Begotten Son, is not to be underſtood
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but perſonally, that 'tis God even the Father.</p>
            <p>So that 'tis deducible from thence, if he will, That the Father who ſent his Son Jeſus, who gave his only Begotten Son, is God; as 'tis deducible from our ſaying the City <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Animal an Horſe, that <hi>Rome</hi> is a City, and a Horſe is an Animal: But it will no more fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, as I conceive, from our ſaying [God the Father] that God is the Father, than from our ſaying the City <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Animal an Horſe, that a City is <hi>Rome,</hi> and an Animal is an Horſe.</p>
            <p>But to give Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> further Scope ſtill, allowing him all that he can poſſibly deſire, That from the Expreſſion [God the Father] this Propoſition may be inferr'd, God is the Father. How will he prove that the Father, in that Propoſition, is the Predicate, and the Term [God] the Subject? For that's the Queſtion betwixt him and the Animadverter. If he will mean no more by it, than that the Father is God: The Animadverter and he are agreed: Which, I doubt, they never will be.</p>
            <p>Hath Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> ſo ſoon forgot, what <hi>he told this great Critick</hi> [the Animadverter] in the beginning of this Page,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:44236:15"/>
               <hi>That tho' the Subject commonly precedes the Verb or Copula, and the Predicate commonly follows, yet this Rule is not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal?</hi> Or ſhall we <hi>find</hi> at laſt that 'tis he himſelf is the Man, <hi>who cannot yet tell when it fails?</hi> Truly 'tis ſomewhat ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicious. For the Particle <hi>The,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd in his Treatiſe of <hi>Engliſh Particles,</hi> anſwers to the Greek Article
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: And 'tis a Queſtion in Logick, <hi>an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulus Graecus ſemper nolet Propoſitionis Subjectum?</hi> Now though it be not univerſally true, that the Greek Article doth denote the Subject of a Propoſition, yet 'tis gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally allow'd, by Logicians and Grammarians, to be a good Rule, to correct the Tranſpoſition or Tranſlocation of the Terms, by attending to the prepoſitive Article; and the Greeks do generally prefix it to the Subject of a Propoſition: And where it is otherwiſe, as ſometimes it may be, it is where the Nature of the Term doth forbid it to be a Subject, which, I am ſure, the Term [Father] here in the Caſe before us doth not.</p>
            <p>To give an Inſtance or two of this. How will M. <hi>J. B.</hi> conſtrue that of <hi>Menander</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; will he conſtrue it, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus eſt Servus Domus Dominus?</hi> I know what the Dr. will ſay to one of your School-Boys that ſhould conſtrue it ſo. But the true Education a Boy hath under him, will teach him to begin with the laſt firſt, with the
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Maſter is one Servant of the Houſe.</hi> So is that of <hi>Plato</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to the Order the Words lie in, to be render'd, <hi>By Nature an uncertain Creature is a Friend:</hi> Though it is the
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is unqueſtionably the Subject of the Propoſition.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> very Soberly and Chriſtianly tells the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverter, <hi>B. ch.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 139. <hi>that he is a great Opiniator, who has forgot his Bible behind him, quite forgot Chriſt and his Twelve Apoſtles.</hi> Againſt which virulent, unchriſtian Charge, I hope, I may be ſecure, by adding to <hi>Menander</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> the Authority of the Holy Book of God, which,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:44236:15"/>I am ſure is fully againſt him in St. <hi>John</hi> 1.1. where we have the true Divinity of the Holy Jeſus thus aſſerted
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Not to take Notice how ſome Hereticks have perverted this Propoſition (concerning which, <hi>vid.</hi> Bp. <hi>Pearſon</hi> on the Creed, <hi>Art.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 120.) it is plain, That the Article
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> prefix'd to the Word
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Place of the Predicate, denotes notwithſtanding the Subject, and accordingly is render'd in our Tranſlation, not according to the Order in which the Words lie, <hi>God was the Word,</hi> but <hi>The Word was God.</hi> So in St. <hi>John,</hi> 4.24. where we have <hi>God,</hi> put in Appoſition to <hi>Spirit</hi> (where the Copula
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> at leaſt, is not expreſs'd but underſtood)
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Though
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> be in the Place of the Subject, yet becauſe it is a Word of a greater Latitude, and the Article
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is put before
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, therefore is it certainly the Predicate; and accordingly our Tranſlators were wiſer than to render it, according to the natural Order of the Words, <hi>a Spirit is God,</hi> but <hi>God is a Spirit.</hi> So that this, I think, may paſs for a Demonſtration of Mr. <hi>J. B</hi>'s conceited Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; and that if he had a Thouſand Expreſſions in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture where the Father is put in Appoſition to God, nay and a Thouſand more, in which there was this very Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in <hi>Terminis</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it would be ſo far from proving what he contends for, that the Father is predicated of God, that it would prove the quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and would unqueſtionably be Tranſlated, <hi>The Father is God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, <hi>But God the Father being</hi> (as Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> ſays) <hi>equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent in Logick to this, That God is a Father,</hi> is it not a very plain Caſe, that <hi>the Animadverter hath not that Skill in Logick he ſo often upbraids others with the want of?</hi> For otherwiſe, it ſeems, <hi>he would have known</hi> that if God be <hi>A</hi> Father, then he is <hi>THE</hi> Father. <hi>God is A Father, and if A Father, THE Father.</hi> Is not this again very Acute and Admirable? What an <hi>Over-grown, Logical-Noddle</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:44236:16"/>muſt this Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> needs have! I dare ſay, there is not an ordinary Logician to be met with but will think, he might as well have inferr'd immediately from the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion God <hi>the</hi> Father, that God is <hi>the</hi> Father, as that God is <hi>A</hi> Father, without being at the abſurd, imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Trouble of proving that God is <hi>the</hi> Father, becauſe God is <hi>A</hi> Father.</p>
            <p>But this, perhaps, was to ſhow, That though <hi>he can freely acknowledge,
<note place="margin">Pref. p. 5.</note> that his Genius (his Education or Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence) never led him to ſtudy Criticiſm in Words, even in his native Language, leſs in the Learned Languages;</hi> yet his Skill in Particles is very critical and extraordinary; and extraordinary, very extraordinary, indeed it is.</p>
            <p>Did you ever hear, Sir, before, or any Man elſe, that if the Particle <hi>A</hi> is prefix'd to a Word, that therefore the Particle <hi>the</hi> muſt? After this Rate, Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> if he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, may prove himſelf to be <hi>the</hi> Writer in this unhappy Controverſy about the Trinity, <hi>the</hi> Writer and none elſe, or <hi>the</hi> Writer
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not excepting <hi>Gilbert</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Sarum,</hi> or his <hi>French</hi> Defender. For <hi>A</hi> Writer he muſt be allow'd to be, ſuch as it is, and if <hi>A</hi> Writer, <hi>the</hi> Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> is an A. M. and Presbyter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſuch an one as he is; doth it therefore follow that he is <hi>THE</hi> A. M. and Presbyter of the Church of <hi>England?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pref. p. 10.</note> God forbid! To prevent this miſchievous Conſequence, I muſt <hi>tell this great Critick,</hi> that 'tis a known Rule in Logick, <hi>à Poſitione Superioris ad Poſitionem Inferioris non valet Conſequentia.</hi> It will follow from the Poſition of [<hi>The</hi>] to the Poſition of [<hi>A</hi>] but not <hi>e con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſo;</hi> that being Diſtinguiſhing, Reſtraining and Definite, this of a greater Latitude and Indefinite. And therefore, though a near Friend of yours be <hi>the</hi> S. Warden of the College, and if <hi>the</hi> S. Warden, no doubt <hi>A</hi> S. <hi>Warden,</hi> yet, I dare ſay, the Reſt of the Fellows will hardly allow that, becauſe your Friend the S. Warden is <hi>A</hi> Fellow, that he is therefore <hi>the</hi> Fellow.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:44236:16"/>
            <p>How happy was it for that Bleſſed Martyr, A. Biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> that Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> was not his Adverſary inſtead of the Jeſuite <hi>Fiſher:</hi> For in his Conference with the Jeſuite [<hi>Confer.</hi> 20.] he allows the Jeſuite that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>A</hi> Church, but not <hi>The</hi> Church. Now if <hi>J. B.</hi> had been to have manag'd the Arch Biſhop, he would have confounded him preſently in two or three Words from his own Conceſſion, <hi>and if</hi> A <hi>Church</hi> The <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now pray, Sir, which do you think would weigh down, if, as he would have it, <hi>Pref. p.</hi> 5. <hi>The Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verter's Criticiſm in Philoſophy and his in Philology were put in the Balance together? But Criticiſm in Philology,</hi> he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes, is not his Talent. <hi>His Genius (his Education or Negligence) never led him to it.</hi> But for Philoſophy and Divinity have at you! the Animadverter is nothing to him. Though for my part, I am apt to think, That though <hi>J. B.</hi> is A. M. and Presbyter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> yet as to theſe [Philoſophy and Divinity] he is, what Holy <hi>David</hi> ſays
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſalm 62.9.</note> of <hi>Men of high Degree, a Lye:</hi> And that when he comes to be laid in the Balance for his Philoſophy and Divinity by the Animadverter, <hi>he will be found to be deceitful upon the Weights, altogether lighter</hi> [than the Animadverter, nay] <hi>than Vanity it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One irrefragable Proof of this, amongſt the reſt, is one of his Scriptural Proofs (which I have not yet taken No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of) that is to ſay, [God is the Father] is no abſurd, il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical Propoſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>St.</hi> Paul <hi>tells us,</hi> ſays he, <hi>That to us there is one God and Father.</hi> Now whether he means, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us this (which is moſt likely) in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. where St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>To us there is but one God the Father, of whom are all things;</hi> or that he tells us this in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.6. (which I ſhall conſider hereafter) where he ſays that <hi>there is one God and Father of all</hi> (for his Words do not exactly agree with either Place, but ſeem to be made up of both; and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:44236:17"/>there is no other Place to which they may be referr'd.) This is moſt certain, that neither Place doth any more prove what he would have, <hi>viz.</hi> That God is the Father, that is, that the Father, the Firſt Perſon of the Bleſſed Trinity, the Father of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> may be properly and Logically predicated of God, than he can prove, that <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> is a Saint (as the poor, ignorant Man thought he was) becauſe he is in the Apoſtles Creed.</p>
            <p>That by the Father here (which he would have to be the Predicate of this Propoſition) he means the Firſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Bleſſed Trinity, the Father of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> there can, I think, be no Diſpute. His Deſign obliges him to mean ſo. Without it he doth not oppoſe the Animadverter: And he himſelf plainly proves that ſo he doth mean, by what he ſays before, and by the Text immediately ſubjoin'd to this, <hi>viz. Bleſſed be God, even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And he means too, That the Father, who is here predicated of God, is not only the Father of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Firſt Perſon of the Ever-Bleſſed Trinity, but that he is predicated of God as diſtinct from the Son and the Holy Ghoſt. For would he ſay or mean that the Father in Conjunction with the two other Bleſſed Perſons is predicated of God, no Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Man, no true Worſhipper of the moſt adorable Trinity would oppoſe him, and the Animadverter ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares himſelf on his Side [<hi>Tritheiſm, p.</hi> 230.] but he, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Sence and Faith of the Holy Catholick Church, of every honeſt, ſimple Chriſtian (of which more by and by) declares, <hi>That the Term [Three intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Perſons] is not adequately and convertibly predicated of God,</hi> that is, That God is not Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt; and that <hi>the ſame Expreſſions of Scripture,</hi> (which prove that the Father is Predicated of God) <hi>confute it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this being undeniably his Sence of the Term [Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther] is it not a moſt unpardonable Blunder in ſuch an
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44236:17"/>Undertaker as this Man is, to prove, that the Father in his Sence is predicated of God, by a Text of Scripture, where, 'tis moſt certain, the Term [Father] is taken in quite ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sence? Is this wiſe Conſiderer of the Doctrine of the Fathers and the Schools, and pretended Baffler of them both, ſo wretchedly ignorant, as not to know that the Term [Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther] attributed to God, is as Homonymous as the Term [God;] and that the Father is taken, as God is, ſometimes
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſometimes
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Word Father, as 'tis taken perſonally, <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ad intra,</hi> in reſpect of his Son begotten of him from all Eternity, for the Firſt Perſon only of the Bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, begetting from all Eternity a Con-ſubſtantial Son; in this Sence, the Father is diſtinct from the Son and the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As the Word Father is taken eſſentially, <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ad extra,</hi> in Reſpect of the whole Creation, for the whole Divine Eſſence; in this Sence, the Father is not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the Son and the Holy Ghoſt; in this Sence, the whole Trinity is the Father, the Son is the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt is the Father: In this Sence is the Word Father ſometimes taken both in the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Certè conſtat,</hi> ſays <hi>Hieron. Zanchius, Nomine Patris non ſemper intelligi in Scripturis Perſonam Patris, ſed totum Deum ipſum Jehovam, Patrem, Filium &amp; Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritum ſanctum. De tribus Elohim,</hi> Par. 2. lib. 5. cap. 5. and in this Sence it is certain is it here taken in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. where St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, That <hi>to us there is but one God the Father.</hi> Let him ſee <hi>Zanchius, loc. citat.</hi> Let him ſee Biſhop <hi>Pearſon</hi> on the Creed, <hi>Art.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 26. Let him ſee Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s Paraphraſe, <hi>Eſtius in loc.</hi> Let him ſee whom he will, he will not find, I dare ſay, ſo much as one honeſt Man that will tell Him, that the Father here is taken, as he takes the Word before, Hypoſtatically, for the Father of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> He might altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44236:18"/>as well, and as effectually, if he had pleas'd, have knock'd down the Animadverter, with the 1ſt. Verſe of the 1ſt. Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> where <hi>Moſes tells us, That in the Beginning God created the Heaven and the Earth.</hi> For this indeed is all that the Apoſtle here tells us, That <hi>to us there is but one God the Father, of whom are all things:</hi> That is, though to the Heathens there are Gods many and Lords many; yet we Chriſtians are aſſur'd they are miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken and are Idolaters; and therefore we acknowledge and believe but one God the Father: <hi>to us there is but one God the Father,</hi> the Father who in the Beginning created the Heaven and the Earth, the Father Almighty (as we profeſs in our Creed) Maker of Heaven and Earth, <hi>of whom,</hi> therefore the Apoſtle adds, <hi>are all things; nimirum per Creationem: Non enim Filium intendit Apoſtolus hâc vice [omnia] comprehendere. Eſtius in loc.</hi> In this Sence of the Word Father all things are of him by Creation and Conſervation, and God is the Father of all things by Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation rather than Procreation, ſays Biſhop <hi>Pearſon loc. ſupr. citat.</hi> and therefore in this Sence our Bleſſed Saviour, the Second Perſon of the Bleſſed Trinity, cannot be of him and cannot be his Son, unleſs Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> will have him to be a Creature, a Factitious, Improper, and Metaphorical God only: And indeed that, I am afraid, will appear at laſt to be at the Bottom of this Man, and to be the grand Deſign and ultimate End of his Book, notwithſtanding its gaudy, deceitful Title, of which more by and by. I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily pray to God that it may appear otherwiſe for his own Soul's Sake, not for any Fear I have that ever he or his Pen will do any great Miſchief to the Catholick Faith, with any who will carefully attend him, and have not a Mind to be perverted. But if Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> means honeſtly, that the Father, which he would have to be properly and naturally predicated of God, is the Father of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Firſt Perſon of the Ever-Bleſſed Trinity,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44236:18"/>diſtinct and only hypoſtatically diſtinct from God the Son, who is one and the ſame true God, of one and the ſame undivided Infinite, Eternal Eſſence with God the Father, then in this Sence, God the Father, in the Paſſage he alledges from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. is not the Father of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> unleſs he will ſay, That God is the Father of us and of all other things, in the ſame Sence, that he is the Father of his only begotten Son our Bleſſed Lord <hi>Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> And then either he muſt ſay, that the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> is a Creature, a Son only in a borrow'd, Metaphorical Sence by Creation, as we and all things elſe are, and as he is ſaid to be the Father of the Rain in <hi>Job</hi> 38.28. or elſe he muſt ſay that God the Father <hi>of whom are all things,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſays, is the Father of all things by a proper, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Generation, as 'tis certain he is the Father of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> And then, which will be the more horrid Blaſphemer, the Animadverter or Mr. <hi>J. B.?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if, to avoid this, he will allow it to be plain, as moſt plain it is, That the Father, in this Paſſage of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> is certainly not to be taken in the Sence he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies it to, <hi>then</hi> plain it is, That this Mighty Divine betrays his groſs Ignorance in a plain Text of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, or, like a mighty pertinent Philoſopher, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes to prove that God is the Father, in a Sence of the Word in which his Adverſary denies it, from a Sence of the Word in which his Adverſary and no Body elſe denies it.</p>
            <p>And thus having, I think, made it very evident to any impartial Reader, how looſely this Man argues, or rather how ridiculouſly he expoſtulates,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.16.</note> inſtead of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with the Animadverter from Scripture; and how like an unlearned Divine and unſtable Chriſtian he wreſts St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Words, where they are not hard to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by every little Novice in Divinity: Let us next conſider, what Reaſon he hath to ſwagger and triumph, at the rate he doth, with his <hi>Logicks,</hi> as he calls it,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44236:19"/>very often in his Book; and ſo 'tis more than probable the Critick writ it in his Copy ſent to the Preſs: For we may not well ſuppoſe that it ſhould be ſo very often Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Logicks, if he had not very often writ it ſo in his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py: and therefore I little doubt, but that it was at laſt put amongſt the Errata and alter'd in his Preface by the Advice of ſome wiſer Friend.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> This terrible Man of Logicks then goes on, and tells us, That <hi>had the Animadverter that Skill in Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick he ſo often upbraids others with the want of, he would have underſtood, that if this Propoſition be true, The Father is God, it is by the Rules of Logick capable of a Converſion, of putting the Predicate in the place of the Subject, and the Subject in the place of the Predicate, without any Alteration of the</hi> Signa Logica [<hi>omnis, nullus, aliquis,</hi> &amp;c.] <hi>where the Subject and the Predicate are both ſingular,</hi> as, ſays he, <hi>I believe them in this Propoſition, [the Father is God] and I have the Conſent of the Schools on my Side:</hi> That is, If the Animadverter had underſtood Logick, he would have underſtood by the Rules of Logick, what by the Rules of Logick he cannot and ſhould not underſtand, and what is directly contrary to the Rules of Logick.</p>
            <p>Had this Logical Braggadochio but a little common Senſe, as well as ſo much Logicks, he would have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that in this very place [<hi>Tritheiſm,</hi> p. 230] where he ſays the Animadverter is guilty of downright Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, in noting this for an abſurd and illogical Propoſition [to ſay that God is the Father] the Animadverter imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſubjoins his Reaſon, why according to the Rules of Logick, it muſt be ſo; becauſe, ſays he, <q>The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate in this Propoſition, [<hi>viz.</hi> God is the Father] is of leſs Compaſs than the Subject, which (where it is not larger) ought to be commenſurate to it at leaſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Had Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> I ſay, but common Senſe, or had he not ſcandalouſly wanted that Skill in Logick, which 'tis
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:44236:19"/>generally believ'd the Animadverter hath, and which, I doubt not, Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> in a ſhort time, will <hi>feel</hi> that he hath, he could not but have ſeen this to be the Animadverter's Reaſon why he could not underſtand that this Propoſition [the Father is God] is by the Rules of Logick converti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by a ſimple Converſion.</p>
            <p>For the Learned Animadverter underſtands well (if Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> does not) that a good and true Converſion muſt contain a good Conſequence of the Propoſition convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Propoſition converted: And that it may do ſo, as the <hi>Conimbricenſes</hi> have ſtated it according to the Sence of all Logicians, it is neceſſary, as they expreſs it, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini non ſumantur in unâ latiùs anguſtiùſve quam in alterâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Logicians are univerſally agreed that the Subject of a Propoſition is always, without any Exception that I know of, a narrower Compaſs than the Predicate, or at leaſt of an equal, but never of a larger. And is not the Predicate in this Propoſition [God is the Father] of leſs Compaſs than the Subject? God is unqueſtionably predicated of Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, but not ſo the Father. Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt are God, is indiſputably a true Catholick Propoſition; but, I hope Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt are the Father, is not ſo. 'Tis the Catholick Faith that the Father is God, the Son is God and the Holy Ghoſt is God; and each Propoſition is infallibly Logical and true: But the Father is not predicated of the Father, but identically; and to predicate him of the Son and of the Holy Ghoſt (as unqueſtionably we may God) that is, to ſay the Son is the Father, as we may ſay the Son is God; and the Holy Ghoſt is the Father, as we may ſay the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt is God, is horridly falſe and damnably Heretical. And can any thing then be plainer, than that the Term [God] is of a larger Compaſs than the Term [the Father?] And if ſo, nothing can be plainer, than that this Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, the Father is God, cannot <hi>by the Rules of Logick,</hi> be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44236:20"/>capable of a ſimple Converſion, of the Tranſpoſition of the Predicate into the place of the Subject, <hi>Salvâ veritate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, but doth the Animadverter underſtand what Mr. <hi>J. B. believes, That in this Propoſition the Father is God, the Subject and Predicate are both ſingular; and that he hath the Conſent of the Schools on his Side?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes, yes! The Animadverter, no doubt, underſtands it very well: He underſtands that God is one or ſingular, as well as that the Father is one or ſingular: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cannot underſtand three diſtinct, infinite Minds, or the Orthodoxy of the admirable <hi>Genebrard</hi>'s Three Gods, no more than he can underſtand that there are three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Fathers. And the Animadverter underſtands too, That as Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> hath the Conſent of the Schools on his Side, that the Father and God are both ſingular; ſo the Animadverter hath the ſame Conſent of the Schools on <hi>his</hi> Side, that as the Father is ſingular <hi>Incommunicably,</hi> ſo God is ſingular <hi>Communicably.</hi> The Father is <hi>ſo Singular</hi> as to be <hi>Incommunicable</hi> to the Son and the Holy Ghoſt, and can therefore be predicated of neither: God is <hi>ſo Singular</hi> as to be <hi>Communicable</hi> notwithſtanding to Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, and can therefore be predicated of all Three <hi>Conjunctly,</hi> and of each of the Three <hi>Diſtinctly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed this is a Communication of one ſingular, undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Eſſence to Three diſtinct Perſons which is moſt my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious, peculiar only to the incomprehenſible God, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be adequately exemplify'd in any thing elſe, and can never be fully comprehended: But yet ſo by divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation infallibly it is. And if God be not a <hi>Terminus Communis</hi> to the Three Divine Perſons, I would fain know, how the Term God can be predicated of the Son and the Holy Ghoſt as well as of the Father; I would fain know, how this Man, denying it, can reconcile his Faith with the Athanaſian Creed, the Father is God, the Son is God, and the Holy Ghoſt is God? Whether by it he doth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:44236:20"/>not bring himſelf under a more unavoidable Dilemma of denying the Divinity of the Son and of the Holy Ghoſt, that the Son is God, and the Holy Ghoſt is God, than the Animadverter doth by denying that God is the Father, of denying the Divinity of the Father, that the Father is God? And whether laſtly it be not an Argument of a <hi>very Peculiar Forehead,</hi> or of ſome very great Defect with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it, for a Man to deny, as this Man does, what is ſo very plain and obvious, that every Body, of common Senſe, who believes the Trinity muſt needs ſee it, and ſee it with that degree of Evidence, as to be as ſure of it as that <hi>Homo</hi> is a common Name to all Men.</p>
            <p>Let this Man ſpeak out and tell us plainly, whether he doth indeed believe, that the Son is God, and that the Holy Ghoſt is God as well as that the Father is God. If he doth, let him tell us then how that 'tis poſſible, if the Name or Term God be not common to all Three.</p>
            <p>What this Man offers againſt this in <hi>p.</hi> 131. and 132. of his Book, is ſilly and ridiculous beyond all Compariſon; beſides what he himſelf affords, and is alone a Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the great Unfitneſs and intolerable Preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Man, to ingage himſelf on this knotty, ſublime Controverſy, and to pretend to chaſtiſe and ridicule the Animadverter and the Schoolmen at the Rate that he doth.</p>
            <p>I ſhall crave your Patience to examine this Matter very particularly, becauſe he lays ſo great a Streſs upon it.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The Term [<hi>Deus</hi>] ſays the Animadverter, is indeed neither a Genus nor a Species. Nevertheleſs all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines and Schoolmen allow it to be a <hi>Terminus Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi>
               </q> And I dare ſay, they do without any Exception, but that of this <hi>J. B.</hi> and ſuch as deny the Divinity of the Son and of the Holy Ghoſt. From hence Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrs, <hi>B.</hi> p. 131. and <hi>finds this great Dictator in Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy</hi> [the Animadverter] <hi>is yet to learn the Firſt Rudiments in Logick.</hi> This he finds and upbraids the Animadverter with very often.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:44236:21"/>
            <p>Now that the Term [<hi>Deus</hi>] is not a <hi>Terminus Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munis,</hi> he undertakes to prove 1ſt. from Logick, in which he ſeems to me to be as great a Conjurer as I am in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick; which I can aſſure you, Sir, I never ſtudied at all. 2dly, from Authority.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt</hi> from his dear Friend Logick. And to ſhew us that he for his part hath enough of it, and that <hi>HE is not yet to learn the Firſt Rudiments in Logick,</hi> as he <hi>finds this great Dictator in Philoſophy</hi> [the Animadverter] <hi>is,</hi> he tells us, <hi>a</hi> Terminus Communis <hi>in Logick, is the ſame with a</hi> Terminus Univerſalis, <hi>with a</hi> Terminus Praedicabilis. This is falſe. Every <hi>Terminus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalis</hi> is a <hi>Terminus Communis,</hi> but not <hi>è converſo.</hi> For what doth he think of an Equivocal Term? <hi>Taurus</hi> is a <hi>Terminus Communis</hi> to a Man, a Beaſt, a Mountain, and to the ſecond Sign in the Zodiack; but I hope he will not ſay it is therefore a <hi>Terminus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalis,</hi> a <hi>Terminus Praedicabilis.</hi> Neither is every <hi>Terminus Praedicabilis</hi> a <hi>Terminus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalis.</hi> Nay, Three of his Five Predicables [<hi>Differentia, propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, accidens</hi>] are not properly Univerſals. But to let this paſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All the Logicians,</hi> he ſays, <hi>he hath had the Fortune to conſult, ſpeak but of Five Predicables,</hi> Genus, ſpecies, Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferentia, Proprium, Accidens. Well, and what then? Why then he hath clearly gain'd his Point: Then (the Animadverter <hi>not being abſurd enough,</hi> he thinks, <hi>to affirm that the Term</hi> Deus <hi>is either</hi> Differentia, Proprium <hi>or</hi> Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and affirming here expreſsly, that it is neither a Genus nor a Species) it clearly follows againſt him, that the Term <hi>Deus</hi> is not a <hi>Terminus Communis.</hi> But if it happen to appear, that it may be and is a <hi>Terminus Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munis,</hi> though it be neither a Genus nor a Species, then the Conſequence is, That this Man by thus fighting in the dark, hath miſs'd the Animadverter, and with one violent Blow hath knock'd down the Platonick Dr. <hi>Cudworth</hi> for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:44236:21"/>he Generical Unity of the Trinity, and for the Specifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Unity his Learned and Acute <hi>Petavius,</hi> and his own more Acute and Learned ſelf in to the Bargain.</p>
            <p>But what is infinitely worſe than all this (and for which he is utterly inexcuſable for venturing concerning this tremendous Myſtery to play at Blindman's-Buff) in foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly attempting to make good his Charge of Blaſphemy againſt the Animadverter, he hath blaſphemouſly Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Son and the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>For if God be not a <hi>Terminus Communis,</hi> it is impoſſible it can be predicated of each of the Three Perſons of the Ever-Bleſſed Trinity, either as a Genus or a Species; and ſo Dr. <hi>Cudworth</hi> and <hi>Petavius</hi> are gone: And if becauſe it is not a <hi>Terminus Communis,</hi> as a Genus or a Species, it therefore can be a <hi>Terminus Communis</hi> no other way, then there's a peremptory End of the Controverſy between the Trinitarians and the Unitarians; the Trinitarians muſt be in the Wrong, and the Unitarians always in the Right. For the Term God cannot be common to Three Perſons; and therefore as there can be but one God, ſo that one God can be but one Perſon: And therefore, according to this his Doctrine [<hi>Horreſco Referens!</hi>] there cannot be God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt; that is, God cannot be truly predicated of each Perſon, for then God would be predicable of more than one, and conſequently a <hi>Terminus Communis</hi> to each Perſon; which, this Man thinks, he hath demonſtrated in about half a Score Lines, that it cannot be.</p>
            <p>After this, I know there can be no need to ſay any thing to his Second Argument from Authority: For we may be ſure he can have none that is good.</p>
            <p>However it is ſo ſuitable to his Argument from Logick, ſo like himſelf, ſo fully decretory againſt the <hi>Converſion</hi> he contends for, and ſuch a clear Juſtification of my Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his Book, the laſt time I was with you, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well paſs it by.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:44236:22"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Then from Authority he proves it plainly thus; <hi>Not one School-man, or Modern who follow them, do, I verily believe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>B.</hi> p. 132. <hi>allow this Term</hi> Deus <hi>to be a</hi> Terminus Communis. He quotes not <hi>one</hi> of theſe School-men or Moderns; (but <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> in the Margin, who is againſt him) and I believe, Sir, you can eaſily gueſs at one very good Reaſon at leaſt, why he doth not.</p>
            <p>Well, but doth not Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> give a Reaſon why he doth verily believe ſo? Yes, he doth ſo: And a very Doughty one it is: As good a Reaſon almoſt as any is in his whole Book.</p>
            <p>I muſt repeat his Words that this Matter may be in the clearer Light. <hi>That famous Objection,</hi> ſays he, <hi>againſt the Faith of the Trinity, which the School-men and Moderns are ſo much concern'd to anſwer, viz. That if the Father is God and the Son is God, the Father muſt be the Son, ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon this Axiom,</hi> Quae ſunt eadem uni Tertio, ſunt eadem inter ſe, <hi>ſhews the Judgment of the School-men and Moderns, that they take this Term</hi> Deus <hi>to be a</hi> Terminus Singularis, <hi>for that Axiom holds not in a</hi> Terminus Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munis.</p>
            <p>Now if this Man had ſtudied Seven Years for't, he cou'd not have found out any thing that makes more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt him; and that ſhews the Judgment of the School-men and Moderns (quite contrary to what he ſays) that they take this Term <hi>Deus</hi> to be a <hi>Terminus Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis;</hi> and for this Reaſon, this very Reaſon, all the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, which my poor Circumſtances and Study will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me, deny that the Axiom holds here.</p>
            <p>No Body, but a Tritheiſt, denies that God is one; that the Divine Eſſence is one ſingular, infinite, undivided Eſſence; and <hi>So</hi> no Body will deny that God is a <hi>Termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Singularis:</hi> But as this <hi>Tertium Singulare</hi> [God] to which the Father and the Son agree, is <hi>Communicable</hi> or rather <hi>Common</hi> to Father and Son; <hi>So</hi> no Body will deny,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:44236:22"/>but this <hi>J. B.</hi> that 'tis a <hi>Terminus Communis:</hi> And upon this very Ground it is, that the <hi>School-men and Moderns are not ſo much concern'd</hi> (as he, like a very ſuſpicious Friend to the Holy Trinity, ſays they are) to anſwer this <hi>Famous Objection againſt the Faith of the Trinity,</hi> but they think it very eaſily and plainly anſwered. <hi>Jam licet Eſſentia Divina ſit Singularis, quia tamen Communicabilis eſt Tribus Perſonis, ideo NON MIR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M eſſe illas Perſonas non eſſe inter ſe idem, etſi Eſſentia idem ſint,</hi> ſays <hi>Stahlius</hi> upon this very Axiom, <hi>Tit.</hi> 18. <hi>Reg.</hi> 2. Nay, I need ſend him no farther than to <hi>Heereboord</hi> upon <hi>Burgerſdicius</hi> (which I hope, I may be allow'd to quote as well as he <hi>Dutrieu,</hi> ſince I am ſure I do it much more to the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) <hi>Inſtitut. Logic. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8. where upon this Rule, he will find theſe Words; <hi>Haec Regula vera eſt, ſi illud Tertium Singulare fuerit Incommunicabile; at ſi fuerit Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municabile, fallit:</hi> And then having propos'd this <hi>Famous Objection</hi> in a Syllogiſm againſt the Faith of the Trinity, grounded upon this Rule, he teacheth every little Freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (that they may not be ſo much concern'd about it, as it ſeems the School men and the Moderns are) thus rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and clearly to anſwer it; <hi>In hoc Syllogiſmo vitium eſt, quod Terminus Medius, ſcilicet Eſſentia Divina, ſit quidem Tertium Singulare, ſed non Incommunicabile; nam Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatur, aut potius COMM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NIS EST, tribus Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this, it can be no wonder (which otherwiſe it juſtly might) to ſee a Paſſage of <hi>Bellarmin</hi> produc'd by him in the Margin as expreſsly againſt him, as he, no doubt, thinks 'tis for him. 'Tis a peculiar way of think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing certainly that this Man hath got; to think that to be for him which every Body elſe muſt needs ſee and think to be againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellarmin</hi> in Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi>'s Margin tells us, that <hi>the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence, though it be ſingular, yet becauſe it is truly in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:44236:23"/>pluribus ſuppoſitis, habet ſe per modum Termini Communis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> doth not deſign by this to ſhew that none but ſuch Blockheads as <hi>Bellarmin</hi> and the Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verter will ſay that the Term [God] is a <hi>Terminus Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munis,</hi> then in this Caſe he takes <hi>Bellarmin</hi> to be his Friend, and inferrs that becauſe the Divine Eſſence <hi>habet ſe per modum Termini Communis,</hi> therefore 'tis not a <hi>Terminus Communis;</hi> which is almoſt as bad as to inferr, <hi>becauſe the Divine Eſſence is a</hi> Terminus Communis, <hi>therefore 'tis not a</hi> Terminus Communis. For allowing that <hi>per modum</hi> may ſometimes ſignifie no more than a Similitude, yet 'tis certain here it ſignifies <hi>ſpecificativè,</hi> by what <hi>Bellarmin</hi> adds afterwards, <hi>quare in Praedicationibus fungitur munere vocis <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalis;</hi> which Office of an Univerſal Word, it is impoſſible it can perform unleſs it be a <hi>Terminus Communis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> ſhould ſay that <hi>per modum</hi> here is taken <hi>per modum Similitudinis;</hi> would it not be very ridiculous for any Man to inferr that therefore he ſays it is not a Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, but only the Similitude of a Similitude. I would deſire Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> to look into <hi>Scheibler</hi>'s Metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicks, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>Tit.</hi> 6. <hi>Art.</hi> 2. (a very uſeful place for him upon other Accounts) where he will find this Phraſe uſed three times within a little Space one of another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Animal,</hi> ſays he, <hi>per modum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalis Communicat ſe Homini.</hi> Will Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> or any Man inferr from hence, that therefore <hi>Animal</hi> is not an Univerſal? And within Four Lines after, he ſays, That an Univerſal is predicated of many Species <hi>per modum Generis:</hi> And of many Individuals <hi>per modum Speciei:</hi> And can any thing but prodigious Ignorance, or Perverſeneſs, conclude from hence, that <hi>Scheibler</hi> aſſerts that an Univerſal which is predicated of many Species is not a Genus; and that an Univerſal which is predicated of many Individuals is not a Species, becauſe he ſays one <hi>habet ſe per modum Generis</hi> and the other <hi>per modum Speciei?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:44236:23"/>
            <p>
               <hi>This indeed,</hi> ſays Mr. <hi>J. B. the School-men and Moderns</hi> (which by what I have ſaid you may be ſure he is inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately well acquainted with) <hi>do hold that this Term</hi> Deus <hi>is a</hi> Terminus Singularis Communicabilis, <hi>Communicable by Predication, as a</hi> Terminus Communis, <hi>but in it ſelf a</hi> Terminus Singularis. Be it ſo. This is enough to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Animadverter's Skill in Logick, and to evince that he may be allow'd to underſtand Logick and to upbraid juſtly Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> with the want of it, though he doth not underſtand that if this Propoſition be true, The Father is God, it is by the Rules of Logick capable of a Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by which he means, as he afterwards explains him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, a ſimple Converſion. For if there be no more in it than this which he allows, That the Term God in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is Communicable by Predication as a <hi>Terminus Communis,</hi> this is enough to make the Propoſition Inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, by the Rules of Logick, of a ſimple Converſion; this is enough to evince that ſuch a Converſion is directly contrary to the Rules of Logick. For 'tis an allow'd Rule in Logick, That <hi>Simplex Converſio non habet Locum in Propoſitionibus Singularibus quatenus Praedicatam eſt Termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Communis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, but, ſays Mr. <hi>J. B.
<note n="*" place="margin">Pref. p. 11.</note> where the Predicate is a</hi> Terminus Communis, <hi>as the Animadverter contends that God is, there a particular Sign is to be added to the Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate when it becomes the Subject, as</hi> Peter <hi>is a Man, ſome Man is</hi> Peter. And upon this, up he gets upon the poor undone Animadverter, and mauls him moſt wofully with a cruel, unavoidable Dilemma; under which he hath him ſo faſt, that now there's no wagging, no Help for him; but <hi>either ſpeak he muſt with the Scriptures, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, the Schools</hi> and Mr. <hi>J. B. in ſaying That God is the Father; or condemn he muſt All Theſe for ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and illogical Dunces</hi> (not only the Schools and Mr. <hi>J.B.</hi> but the Catholick Church and the Scriptures muſt be
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:44236:24"/>condemn'd for abſurd and illogical Dunces. A thing cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly never heard of before.) <hi>And declare</hi> too he muſt, <hi>that we ought to ſay, that ſome particular God is the Father, as ſome particular Man is</hi> Peter. What ſhall this miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly hamper'd Animadverter do! Will he deny the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Father? I hope not. If not, all the Power of Logick cannot relieve him. I [Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi>] <hi>Challenge Him to avoid one of theſe Phraſes, if he can, by the Rules of Logick; unleſs he denies the Divinity of the Father,</hi> and <hi>that,</hi> according to Mr. <hi>J. B</hi>'s Senſe (whatever other Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers and Divines may hold) is to <hi>deny that the Father is God.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pulchrè mehercle Dictum &amp; ſapientèr:
<note place="margin">Teren. Eunuc. <hi>Act</hi> 3. <hi>Scen.</hi> 1.</note> Papae!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jugulâras Hominem: Quid illo? Mutus illico.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>What can the Animadverter ſay to this? Nothing. He muſt certainly be as mute as a Fiſh.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Quid ni eſſet?</hi>—</q>
            <p>It is a great Extremity indeed that a Man muſt be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to, to be forc'd either to ſay that which he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd for abſurd and illogical, or to condemn the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures</hi> for abſurd and illogical Dunces. If the Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verter had been forc'd only to quit his Aſſertion, or to condemn ſome particular Man for an abſurd and illogical Dunce, there might have been no great Occaſion perhaps for a Figure; but to be forc'd to condemn not only the Catholick Church and the Schools, but the Scriptures too; to condemn <hi>All Theſe for abſurd and illogical Dunces;</hi> this is very hard indeed; and he will want ſuch a Figure for the <hi>Phraſe,</hi> as I dare ſay no Author can furniſh him with but Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I hope it may not be altogether ſo bad with the Animadverter as Mr. <hi>J.B.</hi> imagines. If the Animadverter will not quit his Aſſertion (which I believe, upon good
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:44236:24"/>Terms he may, and I doubt not but he will) I hope there will be no Neceſſity of bringing any more than <hi>One</hi> under the aforeſaid Condemnation. I hope it may be ſufficient with the Scriptures, the Catholick Church and the Schools, to give Glory to God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt; and to own and acknowledge, that each Perſon of the Ever-Bleſſed Trinity is God. And if where the Predicate is a <hi>Terminus Communis,</hi> as the Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contends that God is, there a particular Sign is to be added to the Predicate when it becomes the Subject, as <hi>Peter</hi> is a Man, ſome Man is <hi>Peter;</hi> and conſequently that the Animadverter muſt be oblig'd by the Rules of Logick, in the Converſion of this Propoſition [The Father is God] to ſay that ſome particular God is the Father, as ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Man is <hi>Peter,</hi> if there be no Remedy for this; then let Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> firſt clear <hi>the Platonick and Nicene Hypotheſis of the Trinity, which,</hi> as he ſays, <hi>both agreed in this, That the common Divine Eſſence was an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> [<hi>Book p.</hi> 104, 105.] that is, let him clear his juſtify'd Dr. <hi>Cudworth, who embrac'd,</hi> he ſays, <hi>the Platonick Hypotheſis that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence was a Genus:</hi> Let him clear <hi>the Nicene Fathers who,</hi> he ſays, <hi>held the Divinity to be a Species:</hi> Let him clear <hi>all the Greek Fathers, who,</hi> as he ſays from <hi>Petavius, in hoc <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>no Concordant,
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, id eſt, Eſſentiam, ſive Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, ſive Naturam, quam
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> vocant GENERALE ESSE aliquid &amp; Commune ac Minimè DEFINIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M,</hi> [<hi>Book p.</hi> 105.] and <hi>p.</hi> 106. that 'tis <hi>Commune quiddam mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis quod <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſale vocant.</hi> Let him clear his truſty, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd <hi>Petavius,</hi> who, as he ſays, like a true Jeſuite <hi>endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to impoſe upon his Reader what he did not believe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and in his elaborate Work of the Trinity made only a ſeeming Defence for the Faith of the Schools, the Singularity of the common Divine Eſſence, which, upon his Principles,</hi> viz. <hi>the Authority of the Fathers, was impoſſible; and therefore, he ſhamm'd the Notion of the Numerical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in the Room
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:44236:25"/>of it.</hi> This, <hi>p.</hi> 108. is his own Character of his honeſt, dear <hi>Petavius</hi> (with whom he makes ſuch a mighty noiſe throughout his Book) of whoſe Honeſty and Fairneſs (as Acute and Learned as he was) in this Controverſy, let any Man ſee the Account which the Learned Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> gives in his <hi>Defenſ. Fid. Nicaen. Proaem.</hi> p. 7, 8. and then let any honeſt Man value, or truſt <hi>Petavius</hi> afterwards, if he can. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> let him clear his own Hypotheſis, which he ſays <hi>p.</hi> 101. <hi>was the Faith of the Nicene Fathers.</hi> Let him firſt, I ſay, clear all theſe, and then I'll engage to clear the Animadverter, and prove to Mr. <hi>J. B</hi>'s Shame, that if the Animadverter, by only aſſerting that the Term God is a <hi>Terminus Communis,</hi> but no Genus nor Species, is under any Neceſſity by the Rules of Logick, either of Denying that the Father is God, or of declaring in a Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Converſion of the Propoſition, That ſome particular God is the Father, as ſome particular Man is <hi>Peter,</hi> then All Theſe, (who, as he ſtates their Principles, not only aſſert the Divine Eſſence to be Common, but to be an Univerſal, common either as a Genus or a Species) by the ſame Rules of Logick, muſt be under the ſame, if not a much greater Neceſſity.</p>
            <p>In the mean Time, ſince this Man is ſo free of his <hi>Challenges,</hi> let me beg the Favour of you, if you can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly do ſo much for me, to ſend him my Glove as ſoon as you can, and to let him know that if he will ſtand to this, That this Propoſition [The Father is God] is capable of a ſimple Converſion, that is (which is the neceſſary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of it) that the Term [Father] is adequately and convertibly predicated of God: And if upon this, he will ſtand to his Arms in the next Paragraph, by which he thinks he hath given the Animadverter a moſt Fatal and Irrecoverable Overthrow, <hi>viz. That whatever is adequately and convertibly predicated of any Term, may in all Propoſitions be put in the place of that Term;</hi> if he will ſtand to this, I
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:44236:25"/>
               <hi>Challenge him to avoid, if he can, by his own Rules of Logick,</hi> theſe abſurd and intolerably unchriſtian Conſequences, <hi>viz.</hi> That according to this Rule, we may ſay that Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are one Father. In the Beginning was the Word, and the Word was the Father. And (which too will juſtifie the Patripaſſian Hereſie) without Controverſy, great is the Myſtery of Godlineſs, <hi>the Father was manifeſt in the Fleſh, juſtified in the Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. I Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in one Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Father of Father, very Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of very Father. And if it follows from the Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion [God the Father] that God is the Father; then it will follow from theſe Expreſſions [God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt] that God is the Son, and God is the Holy Ghoſt; and then too according to this Rule, we may ſay that the Father is the Son, and the Father is the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>I ſhould not dare, Sir, you may be ſure, to ſend ſuch a bold Challenge to ſuch a deſperate Heroe, who ſo eaſily routs the Animadverter, baffles St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> and, except honeſt, ſtout <hi>Petavius,</hi> and the invincible <hi>Genebrard,</hi> makes all the School-men, and the Moderns too, to ſhrink and <hi>fly before him in their dark and ſlippery way,</hi> as if <hi>the Angel of the Lord drove them:</hi> But never fear your Friend for this, I am very ſure in this I ſhall be too hard for him. This, to brave him once with his own Words, <hi>Pref. p.</hi> 2. <hi>This will ſtill ſtand unanſwer'd, and upon Mr.</hi> J. B's <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples is, I am ſatisfy'd, Unanſwerable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to conclude this Point with his own Gird up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Animadverter [<hi>Book p.</hi> 54.] (which, however ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable it may be to the Animadverter, every Body cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly will allow that it is moſt juſtly and appoſitely ſo to himſelf.) <hi>There is not a ſurer Sign, that an Author does not underſtand the Subject he writes upon, than his bringing an Objection which is ſo plainly and eaſily retorted upon his own Hypotheſis.</hi> And ſuch an Objection is this which I am next to conſider, and is the third thing advanc'd by Mr. <hi>J.B.</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:44236:26"/>againſt the Animadverter, and is urg'd as another Inſtance of the Animadverter's Abſurdity, Heterodoxy, and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy in Divinity; but is a bright Evidence that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is ſcandalouſly Guilty of what he charges the Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verter with, and that he is altogether unfit to be truſted with the Management of ſuch an intricate, ſublime Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy, ſo much above his Learning and Parts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The ſame Expreſſions of Scripture,</hi> ſays Mr. <hi>J. B. confute what the Animadverter tells us, that the Term [Three intelligent Perſons] is adequately and convertibly predicated of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in ſpeaking to this, I ſhall firſt aſſert the Truth of what the Animadverter tells us. And ſecondly, I ſhall weigh Mr. <hi>J.B</hi>'s Objection againſt it. Weigh it did I ſay! 'Tis too great a Solaeciſm. I ſhall ſhew it to have no Weight at all, but to be ridiculouſly abſurd and prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ignorant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall aſſert the Truth of what the Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tells us, that the Term [Three intelligent Perſons] is adequately and convertibly predicated of [God]; that is, that as 'tis true, That the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are God, ſo 'tis as true, proper and Logical to ſay, That God is the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>I cannot pretend to any great Skill in the Fathers and Councils. I muſt own I am as little acquainted with them, as I believe Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> is. I have 'em not, and you know, Sir, that my Circumſtances are ſuch as will not allow me to buy many Books; and that I may truly complain in the Words of the Admirable Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> in the Preface to his <hi>Defenſ. Fid. Nic.</hi> (with the Alteration only of one Word) <hi>Nec potui ipſe, Homo tenui cenſu &amp; Liberis Auctus, Libro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſumptum ſuſtinere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, I hope, there may be no great Occaſion for Fathers and Councils in ſo plain a Caſe as I take this to be, which the Animadverter tells us, and particularly inſiſts
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:44236:26"/>upon againſt the Dean [<hi>Tritheiſm, p.</hi> 230.] and that I may ſafely aſſert it to be the Catholick Faith. <hi>Peter Lombard</hi> I have, who, I think, I may be very ſure, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Catholick Faith much better than Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> doth, or I am afraid ever will: And he not only very fully and expreſsly condemns this bold Man as an <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> to the Truth, but in <hi>Terminis</hi> aſſerts <hi>what the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverter tells us,</hi> to be the Catholick Faith.</p>
            <p>His Words are theſe [<hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Diſtinct.</hi> 4. <hi>Lit. c.</hi>] <q>
                  <hi>Quidam tamen</hi> VERITATIS ADVERSARII, <hi>conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt Patrem &amp; Filium &amp; Spiritum ſanctum, ſive tres Perſonas eſſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Deum, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nam Subſtantiam: ſed tamen</hi> Nolunt Concedere, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Deum ſive <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nam Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiam eſſe Tres Perſonas:</hi> Dicentes Divinam Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam Praedicari de Tribus Perſonis, non Tres Perſonas de Subſtantia Divina. <hi>FIDES autem CATHOLIC A TENET AC PRAEDICAT, &amp; Tres Perſonas eſſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Deum &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nam Subſtantiam ſive Eſſentiam, ſive Naturam Divinam: &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>N<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M DE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M ſive ESSEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIAM Divinam eſſe TRES PERSONAS.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>After this, to confirm what he ſays, he produces ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Paſſages out of ſeveral Places of St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> who fully aſſerts the ſame.</p>
            <p>Thus that Learned Lutheran <hi>Cunradus Dietericus</hi> in his <hi>Inſtitut. Catechet. de Symbol. Apoſtol.</hi> to this Queſtion, <hi>Quis igitur eſt Deus in Eſſentia ſua?</hi> Anſwers, <hi>Eſt Deus Pater, Filius &amp; Spiritus ſanctus.</hi> And a little after in the Explication of this Anſwer hath theſe Words, <hi>Eſſentia nihil aliud eſt, quam illae Tres Perſonae Pater, Filius &amp; Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus ſanctus ſimul junctae; &amp; Perſonae nihil aliud ſunt quam illa ipſa Eſſentia Divina.</hi> So <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin, Explicat. Catechet. Paer.</hi> 2. <hi>ſub Quaeſt.</hi> 25. So <hi>Zanchius, de tribus Elohins Par.</hi> 2. <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 385, 387. So our Holy Mother the Church of <hi>England</hi> (to the Scandal of which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he writes himſelf Presbyter of it) in the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:44236:27"/>Service in the proper Preface for Trinity-Sunday obliges us in the moſt ſolemn Manner, as we are about to take the moſt Bleſſed Sacrament of our Dear Saviour's moſt Precious Body and Blood, to own and declare, That the God, the One God, whom we worſhip is Three Perſons. Nay, (which one that hath not read his Book would hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe) ſo he himſelf tells us expreſsly, That 'tis the <hi>Common Article of the Chriſtian Faith, That God is Three Perſons</hi> [<hi>Book p.</hi> 84.] And what an intolerable Piece of Preſumption then muſt it needs be in this Malapert Man, to aſſert that the <hi>ſame Expreſſions of Scripture confute what the Animadverter tells us,</hi> and what he himſelf tells us <hi>is the Tommon Article of the Thriſtian Faith?</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption <hi>did I call it! It is too mild a Name, I eſteem it a downright Blaſphemy.</hi> What! Do the Expreſſions of Scripture confute the Catholick Faith? Do the Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Scripture confute the great and moſt glorious My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of our Religion, the Doctrine of the Unity in Trinity, and Trinity in Unity; which (as we profeſs in the Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſian Creed) except a Man believe faithfully he cannot be ſav'd? God deliver us from ſuch ignorant, or falſe, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Defenders of the Holy Trinity!</p>
            <p>If we who believe the Trinity in Unity, are oblig'd to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Three Divine Perſons to be One God, why are we not as well oblig'd to believe One God to be Three Perſons, who believe the Unity in Trinity? I have ſhewn Mr. <hi>J.B.</hi> why by the Rules of Logick, the Father cannot be predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated of God, becauſe the Predicate muſt not by the Rules of Logick, be of leſs Compaſs than the Subject. Let him ſhew me, if he can, That the ſame Objection, or any other lies againſt the Three Divine Perſons, being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated of God: And if he cannot (and that I am pretty ſure of) then <hi>the Scriptures,</hi> I hope, <hi>do not confute what the Animadverter tells us;</hi> then (whatever becomes of what Mr. <hi>J.B.</hi> tells us) what the Animadverter here tells
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:44236:27"/>us, ſtands faſt; and I ſhall ever, I hope, believe it, as, I thank God, I always have, not only to be true, but to be the Catholick Faith. For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Reaſon which he offers againſt it, which is the Second Thing to be conſider'd is, as I ſaid before, and ſhall now prove, ridiculouſly abſurd and prodigiouſly ignorant.</p>
            <p>His Reaſon is this, <hi>viz. For whatever is adequately and convertibly predicated of any Term, may in all Propoſitions be put in the place of that Term.</hi> This cannot poſſibly ſerve for any thing but a Rod for his own Breech (which I have made bold to laſh him with before) and expoſe him to the Pity of his Friends, the juſt Cenſure of every judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Reader, and the juſt Scorn and Contempt of his Learned Adverſary.</p>
            <p>How he will avoid the grievous Difficulties he brings himſelf under by this Rule, let him look to't. But that <hi>according to this Rule we may ſay,</hi> as he inferrs from what the Animadverter tells us, <hi>That Three intelligent Perſons ſent his Son, gave his only Begotten Son, that our Saviour is the Son of Three intelligent Perſons. Bleſſed be Three intelligent Perſons, even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> This is ſuch a groſs, wretched Blunder, that, as he truly ſays (not conſidering at all what he ſays) <hi>there needs no Words to expoſe or confute theſe Expoſitions.</hi> No certainly! There needs none for any Body but himſelf.</p>
            <p>And is it not great Pity, Sir, and a Scandal to our Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities and Church, that there ſhould be ſuch an A. M. and Presbyter of the Church of <hi>England</hi> as <hi>J. B.</hi> who wants to be told, That Three Divine Perſons are not One Divine Perſon, and that One Divine Perſon is not the Three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons? That the Perſons Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are not the Perſon of the Father, and that the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Father is not the Perſons of Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt? What a ſtrange Stupor is this, that this Man
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:44236:28"/>labours under! And yet muſt needs be writing of Books, and Books of the Bleſſed Trinity too. Is it poſſible for any Man to be ſo blind, ſo very hebetious, as not to ſee plainly, that the Term [God] of which the Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſays the Term [Three intelligent Perſons is adequately and convertibly predicated] is not taken perſonally for God the Father? It is impoſſible it ſhould be ſo taken, unleſs we can ſuppoſe that the Animadverter's Aſſertion is, That the Three intelligent Perſons are adequately and convertibly predicated of God the Father, the Firſt Perſon of the Bleſſed Trinity. If not, if the Term [God] be not taken by the Animadverter perſonally for God the Father, but <hi>Eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi> for God as Common to Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, as moſt evidently it is, then allowing this Rule; that whatever is adequately and convertibly predicated of any Term, may in all Propoſitions be put in the Place of that Term, how could any thing but the moſt ſtupid Ignorance inferr from hence, that <hi>according to this Rule we may ſay, That Three intelligent Perſons, ſent his Son, gave his only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son,</hi> &amp;c. when nothing can be more manifeſt that Three intelligent Perſons are not here, in any of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances he gives, put in the place of that Term [God] as 'tis taken by the Animadverter Eſſentially and Indefinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as the Term God, that is, is common to all the Three Divine Perſons, and is truly predicated of them <hi>ſimul ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptis:</hi> But they are put by him in the place of the Term [God] in a Sence in which it is moſt certain the Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verter doth not mean it, that is, as God is taken definite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and perſonally for God the Father. For God who ſent his Son, gave his Son, and is the Father of our Lord <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> is not God, I hope, as the Term ſignifies the whole Trinity, all the Three Divine Perſons, but as it ſignifies perſonally, the Firſt Perſon of the Bleſſed Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, God the Father diſtinct from God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt: And therefore it is moſt manifeſt, That
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:44236:28"/>it can no more follow, according to this Rule, from what the Animadverter tells us, that we may ſay, That Three intelligent Perſons ſent his Son, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than it can follow, that becauſe Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are God, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are God the Father.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The oftner I read theſe Words</hi> (as he expreſſes himſelf againſt the Animadverter [<hi>Book p.</hi> 153.] and nothing can be more proper and ſuitable than to rebuke him with his own uncircumcis'd Lips) <hi>the more I admire at the preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous Confidence of him that wrote them. I am ſure no Man can give a more convincing Argument of his utter unacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the Principles of all Philoſophy and Divinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This indeed is a Demonſtration to me, That this Mr. <hi>J.B.</hi> either wants common Senſe, or common Honeſty; or that he is utterly ignorant of the well-known Homonymy of the Term [God] that in its proper Acceptation, it is ſometimes taken abſolutely, indefinitely, or (as ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it) ſimply and (as the School men generally expreſs it) eſſentially. In this Senſe it is taken for the Divine Eſſence, which is Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt; or, as <hi>Zanchius</hi> expreſſes it [<hi>De tribus Elohim, Par.</hi> 1. <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 259.] <q>
                  <hi>Pro toto, ut it a loquar, Deo, pro<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina Eſſentia, ſeu pro Deitate, quae nihil eſt aliud, quam Deus ipſe totus, Pater, Filius, Spiritus ſanctus.</hi>
               </q> And in this Senſe, it is manifeſt, the Animadverter takes the Term [God] in what he tells us. Sometimes again the Term [God] is taken definitely, diſtinctly, or (as ſome expreſs it) <hi>Secundum Quid,</hi> (or as the School-men gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſpeak) perſonally. In which Senſe, it is taken when it is predicated only of ſome certain Perſon of the Trinity, ſometimes of the Perſon of the Father only, ſometimes of the Son only, and ſometimes of the Holy Ghoſt only, in which diſtinct, perſonal Senſe it is manifeſt that God is to be taken in the Expreſſions of Scripture, which he here alledges, when it is ſaid God ſent his Son, gave his only
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:44236:29"/>begotten Son, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that is, God the Father, as he himſelf before determines: And in this Senſe, it is as manifeſt that the Animadverter doth not take it, in what he here tells us.</p>
            <p>So that this Man muſt ſay, either that he well knew in his Conſcience that this which he urges here againſt the Animadverter is a <hi>Non ſequitur,</hi> a mere <hi>Sophiſmo Home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymiae,</hi> and that he intended only in Imitation of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Petau,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Book p. 108.</note> to <hi>ſham his Reader,</hi> to put a pitiful, little Trick upon him, which is not well conſiſtent with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Honeſty; or elſe I <hi>muſt</hi> ſay that he is ſcandalouſly ignorant: And ſo like thoſe conceited Gnoſticks St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, who prided themſelves in their great Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge above that of other Men, and ſuppos'd all other ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant but themſelves, <hi>If this Man</hi> vainly <hi>thinketh he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any thing,</hi> I have too much reaſon to tell him, <hi>he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing yet as he aught to know,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi>'s Paraph. in Loc.</note> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.2. And yet the Homony my of the Term [God] (which there is hardly, I think, any little Novice in Divinity, that is not leſs than himſelf, but knows) <hi>is,</hi> to uſe his own Words, <hi>Pref. p.</hi> 3. <hi>a very neceſſary Matter to be known by all who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to give us an Hypotheſis to ſolve the ſacred Myſtery of the Trinity [to do otherwiſe is</hi> (if any thing be) <hi>to make a Key for a Lock by the Key-hole only: Such a Key is a mere Shew, 'tis Ten Thouſand to One, that it never fits the Wards.</hi>]</p>
            <p>In this very Paragraph, <hi>Pref. p.</hi> 3. from whence I bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row theſe Words for him, it may be worth your while, Sir, a little to obſerve this <hi>Thraſo</hi> (that you may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter know the Man) ſtrutting like a Crow in a Gutter, or like a Cock-Turkey letting down his Wings and raiſing his Plumes to make himſelf as big again as really he is, thus diſplaying his intolerable Vain-Glory.</p>
            <p>I [Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi>] <hi>I Diſcuſs that Important and Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Enquiry in this Myſtery,</hi> viz. <hi>What is it whish determines
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:44236:29"/>the Singularity or Plurality of the Predication of any Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute concerning the Divine Perſons: Where I</hi> [Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> by himſelf] <hi>firſt give the Predications themſelves which are to be ſolv'd. A very neceſſary Matter,</hi> &amp;c. ut ſupr. <hi>Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I Conſider the Anſwers of the Schools and ſhew their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency. Laſtly, I endeavour to give the true Solution My Self:</hi> Beſides Six great Things which <hi>I</hi> doth before, and a great many ſtrange Exploits which <hi>I</hi> doth after.</p>
            <p>And now to ſerve him again with his own Words [<hi>Book p.</hi> 139.] (for which I muſt confeſs I am often mightily beholden to him, they are ſo very pat for him) <hi>Make Room for this mighty Man, keep Silence, and learn from him, what the ignorant Animadverter,</hi> the trifling St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> the impertinent School-men, and the ſilly, ſottiſh, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derns, their Followers, could never teach you before.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Polo deripere Lunam vocibus poſſum meis:</hi>
            </q>
            <p>So, as <hi>Horace</hi> hath it ſomewhere in his Epiſtles, the Witch <hi>Canidia</hi> boaſts. But they were but Words I trow. Juſt ſuch vain, impotent Braggs as Mr. <hi>J. B</hi>'s are. He do thoſe things, he ſo vauntingly tallis of! So could the Hag <hi>Canidia</hi> with her conjuring Words, ſnatch the Moon from her Pole: So could <hi>Quintus Serenus</hi> cure an Ague with his proud, cramp Word ABRACADABRA.</p>
            <p>After all, I am afraid, as I hinted before, that there is ſome lurking Evil, ſome ſly Deſign in this Book, which ſome may not be aware of. I am afraid, that beſides the many Follies, Impertinencies, Miſtakes, Abſurdities and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions with which his Book abounds, we have a Lap-full of wild Gourds, and that there is Death in the Pot
<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Rings,</hi> 4.39, 40.</note> For he ſeems to me not only to do what he can to puzzle the Cauſe, and ſlily to undermine the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith of the Unity in Trinity, and the Trinity in Unity; but he plainly betrays it, and roundly gives it up
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:44236:30"/>to thoſe abominable Hereticks whom he pretends to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>That this he doth, I ſhall undertake now to make out very fully and plainly, and is the laſt thing I ſhall trouble you with about him.</p>
            <p>In the Preface here, <hi>p.</hi> 10, 11. he undertakes to prove by Scripture and by Logick, That God is the Father, that 'tis Blaſphemy to deny it: That if this Propoſition be true, [the Father is God] it is by the Rules of Logick capable of ſuch a Converſion, as that 'tis as true to ſay, that God is the Father as that the Father is God; that is, That One Perſon is adequately and convertibly predicated of God, that is, by neceſſary Conſequence, that God is One Perſon: And that he is <hi>But</hi> One Perſon, and that there's no ſuch thing as this Trinity of Divine Perſons, according to the Senſe of the School-men and Moderns, and the Holy Catholick Church, and our Holy Mother the Church of <hi>England,</hi> he tells that the Term [God] is a ſingular Predicate; that it is not a <hi>Terminus Communis,</hi> as fooliſh Chriſtians do generally believe it; that is, That God is not common to Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, but adequately and convertibly predicated of the Father only: And therefore, very conſequently to this he tells us very roundly, that 'tis falſe, and the Expreſſions of Scripture confute it, to ſay that the Term [Three intelligent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons] is adequately and convertibly predicated of God; for that would be utterly inconſiſtent with, and contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory to the Fathers, being adequately and convertibly predicated of the ſame God, that is, 'tis falſe, and the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Scripture confute it,</hi> to ſay, That the One Holy and Eternal God whom we Worſhip is Three intelligent Perſons, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Let him clear himſelf and prove, if he can, that I do not expound him, honeſtly, juſtly, and fairly. If I do not it is very unwittingly and unwillingly, God knows.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:44236:30"/>
            <p>And is not this Man then a choice Conſiderer of the Doctrine of the Fathers, and the Schools concerning the Trinity? Is not this an admirable Champion of the Holy Catholick Faith? A precious Defender of the Reverend Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s? I hope the Reverend Dean did not give any thing for him, or fetch him far. If he did I am ſure he hath bought him very dear. But I hope (and I cannot but believe it) that though this Book was Printed for the Dean's Bookſeller, the Dean knew nothing of it, at leaſt did not peruſe it till 'twas Printed.</p>
            <p>It is very plain, I think, That this Man, under a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of defending the Doctrine of the Bleſſed Trinity, doth either ignorantly or treacherouſly expoſe and betray it. It is very plain, here in his Preface, that his Doctrine is, that God is the Father, and is not Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, that is, That God is one Perſon and is not Three Perſons; and therefore this muſt be allow'd as a very proper, ſuitable Preface to his Book, in which he makes it yet plainer, if it be poſſible, that this is his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and gives it us as his Creed [<hi>ch.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 18. <hi>p.</hi> 84.] in this Form; <hi>I Believe that the God whom the Heathen Philoſophers by the Light of Nature worſhipped was One Divine Perſon. I Believe that the ſame One Divine Perſon ſpake of himſelf in theſe ſacred Words of the Law, I am the Lord thy God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I alſo Believe, That this One Divine Perſon was the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is his Confeſſion of Faith (which we ſhall have by and by delivered in another Explanatory Symbol) and I'll engage that there is not a Man upon the Earth, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves that there is but One true God; and that there was ſuch a Perſon upon Earth as <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> let him be Jew, Gentile, Arian, Sabellian, Socinian, what he will but will freely join with him in it and ſubſcribe to it. Agreeably to this Faith, he thinks fit to <hi>Curry</hi> a little and Declare [<hi>B. p.</hi> 100.] that <hi>he is not for Perſecution, no, not of the Socinians.</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:44236:31"/>'Tis very ſtrange if he ſhould. I'll warrant him a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſwinging Latitudinatian. I am not my ſelf for Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution in the true Senſe of the Word; but yet I am not for ſetting aſide the penal Laws and Teſt: I am for keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the Hedges of our Vineyard (if the good God ſo pleaſe) that all they that go by, may not pluck off her Grapes; that the wild Boar out of the Wood may not root it up, and the wild Beaſts of the Field devour it
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſalm 80.12, 13.</note>. And I am clearly, inſtead of truſting them and letting them in by any falſe, treacherous Comprehenſion, for taking the Foxes, the little Foxes that ſpoil the Vines
<note n="*" place="margin">Cant. 2.15.</note>. And I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily thank God for't, there is <hi>yet</hi> a great Body of honeſt, learned, good Men, who value the Honour and Good of the Church of <hi>England</hi> above all politick, worldly Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations whatſoever, of my Opinion.</p>
            <p>But to return to this Comprehenſion-Man's Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive Creed, which will give as great a Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, if not a greater, as ever the late King <hi>James</hi> aim'd at in his Declaration, (whereby to do <hi>HIS</hi> Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in one Senſe, and <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RS</hi> in another) and will compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend as many as the licentious Author of a late Letter for Toleration can poſſibly deſire,) though he doth <hi>Believe that the God whom the Heathen Philoſophers by the Light of Nature worſhipped, was One Divine Perſon:</hi> And though he doth <hi>Believe that the ſame One Divine Perſon ſpake of himſelf,</hi> that is (I ſuppoſe you will allow me he means) of himſelf as One Divine Perſon: And though he <hi>doth Believe that this One Divine Perſon was the Father,</hi> &amp;c. yet he tells you there, <hi>he doth moſt firmly believe, that the Faith of a Trinity of Divine Perſons and the Article of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of God</hi> [<hi>As it was Believ'd by the wiſeſt of the Heathens and the Jewiſh Church</hi>] [who Believ'd God to be but One Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſon] <hi>are by no means inconſiſtent. Nor does this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict that common Article of the Chriſtian Faith,</hi> viz. <hi>That God is Three Perſons, as the Socinians vainly pretend, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:44236:31"/>ſome others unwarily grant them.</hi> Good God! What ſtrange Deluſions are ſome Men given over unto,
<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.11.</note> that they ſhould believe a Lye! 'Tis very true what Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> ſays [<hi>Book p.</hi> 158.] <hi>That ſome Perſons take a Privilege to ſpeak and write what they pleaſe:</hi> And certainly never any Man made more Uſe of this Privilege than himſelf.</p>
            <p>Do the Socinians vainly pretend, that it is a Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for One and the ſame God to be but One Perſon, and yet to be Three Perſons? If it be not a Contradiction, I do averr that nothing can be ſo. <hi>Some,</hi> he ſays, <hi>do unwarily grant the Socinian that it is a Contradiction;</hi> as if ſome others or rather the moſt do not. What a vile Reflection is this upon the Orthodox, nay upon Mankind! Let him name me a Chriſtian, or a Man beſides himſelf that will ſay that [One Perſon is Three Perſons] is no Contradiction. We have been ever able, and ever ſhall, to defend the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith, That One and the ſame God is Three Perſons, from being a Contradiction; and therefore, though it be a great and incomprehenſible Myſtery, yet we moſt firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe it as clearly revealed to us in Scripture, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the conſtant Interpretation given of it by the Holy Catholick Church down to theſe Days: But to ſay that One and the ſame Perſon is Three Perſons, is to ſay that One and the ſame is not One and the ſame; and that Three Perſons are not Three Perſons but One Perſon, and is therefore ſuch a Contradiction as is impoſſible to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd by God, that cannot lye, and impoſſible to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended. Let Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> if he pleaſes, try what he can do.</p>
            <p>Now if One and the ſame God, who <hi>was</hi> and is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> is the ſame One God whom the Heathen Philoſophers and the Jews worſhipped (as no doubt he is;) and if this One God <hi>was</hi> One Divine Perſon (which, no doubt, he was not, though believed and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped by them but as One Perſon, and that without He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, God having not made ſo full a Revelation of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:44236:32"/>under that Oeconomy as under the Chriſtian) and if Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> doth moſt firmly believe, as he ſaith he doth, that the Faith of a Trinity of Divine Perſons and the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Unity of God, <hi>AS</hi> it was believ'd by the wiſeſt of the Heathens and the Jewiſh Church (who believ'd the One God to be <hi>but</hi> One Divine Perſon) <hi>are by no means inconſiſtent;</hi> then either he muſt ſay that the ſame God, who <hi>was</hi> but One Divine Perſon is now, ſince Chriſtianity, become Three Divine Perſons, which is utterly inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with his immutable Nature; or that the ſame One Divine Perſon was and is Three Divine Perſons, which is a Contradiction; or laſtly, that <hi>that one Divine Perſon whom the Heathens and Jews worſhipped, was and is the One only true God;</hi> And as for the other Two Divine Perſons, the Son and the Holy Ghoſt, which with that One Divine Perſon which the Heathens and Jews worſhipped, and who is the <hi>One only true God,</hi> make up a Trinity of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons; the Term God may indeed be predicated of them, but not ſtrictly, properly and truly, as it is of God the Father. For though there be a Trinity of Perſons call'd Divine, yet 'tis God the Father <hi>whom the Heathens and Jews worſhipped is the One only True God:</hi> and <hi>SO the Faith of a Trinity of Divine Perſons and the Article of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of God [as it was believed by the wiſeſt of the Heathens and the Jewiſh Church] are by no means inconſiſtent:</hi> And ſo perhaps honeſt <hi>Genebrard</hi>'s Three Gods and the Quaſi-Specifical Unity is made out in to the Bargain. For, tho', as Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> ſaith [<hi>ch.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 19. <hi>p.</hi> 85.] <hi>The Reverend Dean never aſſerted that the Son or Holy Ghoſt could not be properly call'd the One God, or only True God;</hi> yet he [his noble Defender] dares to do what the Dean durſt not: he can and will aſſert it. <hi>I,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>p.</hi> 86. <hi>do aſſure him</hi> [the Animadverter] <hi>that I am neither afraid of him, nor the Socinians; I crave no Favour at either of their Hands for This Profeſſion of my Faith, that the Title of One
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:44236:32"/>God, only True God, is a proper, perſonal Prerogative of the Father Alone.</hi> Now 'tis out.</p>
            <p>Now you ſee clearly why he will have the Term God, in the Preface, to be adequately and convertibly predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated of the Father, and will not allow it [the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, he ſaith, confute it] to be adequately and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibly predicated of Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Certainly, whatever Occaſion this Man may have to be <hi>Afraid</hi> of the Animadverter, he can have none at all to be <hi>Afraid</hi> of the Socinians, unleſs it be as the Pſalmiſt ſays, That they ſhould laugh him to Scorn
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſalm 80.6.</note>, for pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be their Adverſary: For ſuch a Trinity as this is, it is certain the Socinians, who are the Followers of <hi>Bidle,</hi> do believe and contend for.</p>
            <p>If the Title of <hi>One God, only True God,</hi> be <hi>appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and peculiar only to the Perſon of the Father, a proper, perſonal Prerogative of the Father Alone;</hi> then let any Man prove, if he can, That the Son or the Holy Ghoſt is properly God, unleſs he can prove that there be more Gods than one.</p>
            <p>Let Mr. <hi>J.B.</hi> with all his Logicks and vaſt Stock of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon prove, if he can, That this <hi>Profeſſion of his Faith</hi> is not by his own Confeſſion, worſe than Socinian, worſe than <hi>Nine Parts in Ten of the Objections of the Socinians, which,</hi> ſaith he, [<hi>Book p.</hi> 173.] <hi>are not levell'd againſt the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Truth of this Article, the true Divinity of each ſingle Perſon</hi> [of the Bleſſed Trinity.] If, as he ſays, <hi>he plainly ſees</hi> that Nine Parts in Ten of the Objections of the Socinians are not levell'd againſt this Fundamental Truth, he might, one would think, if he had not wink'd hard, have <hi>ſeen as plainly</hi> that this Profeſſion of his Faith is <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly</hi> levell'd againſt it.</p>
            <p>For is it not moſt ridiculouſly abſurd, a monſtrous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, to aſſert the true Divinity of each ſingle Perſon of the Bleſſed Trinity, and yet to deny that the Son, or the Holy Ghoſt may be call'd True God? But if it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:44236:33"/>and peculiar to the Father <hi>alone,</hi> to be the One God, the only True God, it is demonſtrable that neither the Son nor the Holy Ghoſt can be ſo: Unleſs the Father <hi>Alone</hi> can be the One God and not the One God, the <hi>only</hi> True God and not the <hi>only</hi> True God. And therefore I'll be bold to challenge this mighty Challenger to clear, if he can, <hi>this Profeſſion of his Faith</hi> from being a monſtrous Contradiction, or a monſtrous Hereſie.</p>
            <p>It will nothing avail him to ſay, That 'tis the <hi>Title</hi> of One God, <hi>only</hi> True God which he aſſerts to be the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, perſonal Prerogative of the Father <hi>Alone.</hi> For if the Father <hi>alone</hi> be not <hi>Revera</hi> the One God, the <hi>only</hi> True God, it cannot be the <hi>proper, perſonal Prerogative of the Father alone</hi> to be ſo call'd, unleſs we will lye for the Father, and ſay that he <hi>alone</hi> is what <hi>alone</hi> he is not. What is proper and perſonal, in Divinity and common Senſe, is incommunicable; and therefore if to be One God, <hi>only</hi> True God be the <hi>proper</hi> and perſonal Title of the Father <hi>alone,</hi> the Father <hi>alone</hi> muſt enjoy it: Neither Son nor Holy Ghoſt can have it; nor can it be predicated of the whole Trinity, unleſs the Father <hi>alone</hi> is the whole Trinity.</p>
            <p>It is plain therefore, if any thing by Words can be ſo, That this Man according to this his publick Profeſſion of Faith, doth deny the Catholick Doctrine of the Bleſſed Trinity, which he falſly and inſidiouſly, or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, by the gaudy, pompous Title of his Book, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to defend. For he denies the Father, Son, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt to be <hi>One God, the only True God.</hi> For if they [the Three Divine Perſons] be truly and properly <hi>One God, the only True God,</hi> no Man living, I ſuppoſe, will deny but that they may <hi>truly and properly</hi> be ſo call'd. And he denies the <hi>true</hi> Divinity of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt. For if the Father <hi>alone</hi> be One God, <hi>only</hi> True God; how can the Son be God and the Holy Ghoſt be God, <hi>but impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and metaphorically? True</hi> God (according to this
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:44236:33"/>Man's Principles) neither of them can be; for the <hi>only True</hi> God is the Father <hi>alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is this Mans Faith, according to the defying pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Profeſſion which he here makes of it.</p>
            <p>And to make himſelf the more blaſphemous, more abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, and inexcuſable, he quotes and brings in with unparallell'd Ignorance and Confidence, 1ſt. The Nicene Council. 2dly, All the Oriental Fathers. 3dly, Our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour. 4thly, St. <hi>Hilary,</hi> and 5thly, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to abett, and patronize him in it. [<hi>Book p.</hi> 85.]</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> As for the Nicene Council, which, he ſays, <hi>appropriates this Title to the Father:</hi> What can be more falſe and impoſing? <q>
                  <hi>Credimus in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Deum, Patrem Omnipotentem, &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nigenitum Filium ejus Jeſum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum, &amp; Spiritum ſanctum. Non Tres Deos, fed Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem, Filium &amp; Spiritum ſanctum</hi> Unum Deum <hi>colimus &amp; confitemur. Non ſic</hi> Unum Deum, <hi>quaſi</hi> Solita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</q> 
               <hi>&amp;c. Lamb. Danaei Expoſ. Symb. Apoſt. ex Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trib. Orthodox. Art.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 6, 7. where he may find Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities enough, out of the Fathers, againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Credo in Deum. Nomen Dei hic ſumitur</hi> eſſentialiter <hi>pro Deo Patre, Filio &amp; Spiritu ſancto: Quia verbum [Credo] cum Particula [in] refertur</hi> eodem modo <hi>ad omnes Tres Perſonas Deitatis. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin. in Explicat. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techet. Par.</hi> 2. <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 26.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He will not deny, I believe, that the Term [God] in the Apoſtles Creed is taken in the ſame Senſe with that in the Nicene; for that Biſhop <hi>Pearſon</hi> upon the Creed has obſerv'd, <hi>Art.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 23. <q>That this Creed in the Churches of the Eaſt, before the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> had that Addition in it [I believe in <hi>One</hi> God] <q>that is, ſays Dr. <hi>Comber, I confeſs with my Mouth, That I believe in my Heart in One God, a pure and infinite Spirit, diſtinguiſhed into Three Perſons, the Firſt of which is God the Father,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Compan. to the Temple,</hi> Part 3<hi>d.</hi> S. 5.</q>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:44236:34"/>
            <p>And therefore ſays <hi>Zanchy,</hi> moſt fully and expreſsly againſt what this Man aſſerts; to prove from the Creed that 'tis the Father <hi>alone</hi> who is the One God, is a mere <hi>Fallacia Compoſitionis,</hi> which the Hereticks make uſe of to prove their and this Man's Faith from the Creed, <q>
                  <hi>Quam ſcilicet conjungunt in oratione quae ſunt diſtinguenda; ut verbi gratia, quum probant, ideo</hi> Solum <hi>Patrem eſſe Deum</hi> verum <hi>quia in Symbolo legimus,</hi> Credo in Unum Deum Patrem. <hi>Hic enim conjungunt Nomen Patris cum Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Dei, nullam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> interponunt diſtinctionem inter Dei &amp; Patris Nomen, cùm tamen diſtinctè ita legendum eſſe vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur, ut primo dicatur in genere,</hi> Credo in Deum; <hi>poſtea vero per Perſonas,</hi> quaſi <hi>per partes explicetur, quis ſit iſte Deus, nempe Pater, Filius &amp; Spiritus ſanctus. Hi enim Tres Elohim ſunt</hi> ceu <hi>partes non totales fed eſſentiales
<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vae. Hieron. Zanch. de Tribus Elohim, Par.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 383.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I am almoſt confident that this intolerably bold Man, cannot produce ſo much as one Author who ſo interprets the Beginning of the Nicene Creed, that the Title of One God is <hi>appropriated</hi> to the Father, in Oppoſition to the Son and the Holy Ghoſt. And as the One God is not appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated in that Creed to the Father, but referrs to all the Three Perſons, ſo neither is the Title of <hi>only True</hi> God: But this very Creed which this frontleſs Man quotes for him, is expreſsly full and decretory againſt him; and not only calls the Second Perſon [the Son] God of God, but <hi>very God</hi> of very God,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Deum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum de Deo vero,</hi> True God of True God. And is it not very likely now, that all the Oriental Fathers, and our Bleſſed Saviour ſhould determine for him againſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Words of the Nicene Creed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As for <hi>All the Oriental Fathers</hi> [every one of them, no doubt, he hath read and underſtands throughly well] we muſt take his Word that what they ſay in the Nicene Creed, they do <hi>not</hi> ſay nor believe. Theſe are ſome of the Fruits of <hi>Haſty Births.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:44236:34"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As for our Bleſſed Saviour, he faith indeed, St. <hi>John</hi> 17.3. <hi>This is Life eternal that they might know thee the only True God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</hi> But doth it follow from hence, that our Saviour appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates this Title of <hi>only True God</hi> to the Perſon of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Never any Body that I can find made ſuch an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference but the worſt of Hereticks, and with them indeed nothing is more frequent. He cannot, I dare ſay, name me one Heretick Author who denies the Doctrine of the Bleſſed Trinity, but what urges theſe Words of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to prove the very thing he contends for. <q>
                  <hi>Parolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmus Secundus, iſque</hi> Frequentiſſimus, ſays <hi>Zanchy [de Tribus Elohim, par.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 382, 383.] <hi>eſt
<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, quum ſcilicet argumentantur ex Scripturarum locis qui multiplicem poſſunt habere ſenſum: Ipſi vero Haeretici illum arripiunt, qui ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cum aliis Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cum analogia Fidei eſt conſentaneus. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t, verbi gratiâ, quum probant</hi> Solum <hi>Patrem</hi> ideo <hi>eſſe</hi> Illum Unum Deum, <hi>&amp;c. quia dixit Chriſtus,</hi> haec eſt vita aeterna, ut cognoſcant te ſolum verum Deum &amp; quem miſiſti Jeſum Chriſtum, <hi>Jo.</hi> 17.3.</q> Now that what the Hereticks and Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> contend for, doth not follow from hence, he thus goes on clearly to evince;
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>eſt in his verbis, Poteſt enim illud</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] &amp;c. I ſhall tranſlate his following Words exactly into Engliſh
<note n="*" place="margin">Poteſt enim illud [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] referri ad Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectum, id eſt, ad l'atrem, ut ſit ſenſus, ſolum Patrem eſſe verum Deum; vel ad Praedicatum, ut ſit ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, Patrem eſſe illum Deum verum qui iolus &amp; unus eſt. Hic alter ſenſus &amp; meliùs convenit cum ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctura verborum &amp; conſentancus eſt cum aliis Sacris Literis. Neque enim <hi>propterea</hi> negatur Filius eſſe verus ille Deus, qui ſolus &amp; unus eſt, <hi>quia hoc</hi> ibi af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatur de Patre: Id quod etiam <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> obſervavit, <hi>contra Gentil. Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 8. Deinde eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amſi admittatur Prima Lectio, poteſt tamen bifariàm intelligi, nempe, aut Solum Patrem <hi>ita</hi> eſſe verum Deum, ut excludatur Filius &amp; Spiritus ſanctus: Sed hic ſenſus cum aliis Scripturis non congruit. Aut ut alia tantum omnia, quae non ſunt ejuſdem cum Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre eſſentiae, negentur eſſe Deus. Atque hic ſenſus cum aliis Scripturis pulchrè convenit.</note>. <q>That Word [only] may be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Subject, that is, to the Father; ſo as that the Senſe may be <hi>the Father only is the True God:</hi> Or to the Predicate, ſo as that the Senſe may be, <hi>the Father is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:44236:35"/>that True God who is Alone and One.</hi> This latter Senſe doth both better agree with the Contexture of the Words, and is more agreeable with other places of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture: <hi>And therefore it is not here denied that the Son is that True God who is alone and One, becauſe this is affirm'd</hi> here of the Father. The very ſame hath <hi>Thomas Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> obſerv'd, <hi>contra Gentil. Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 8. Again, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the firſt Reading of the Words, and then the meaning muſt be, That the Father only is the True God, either <hi>ſo</hi> as to exclude the Son and the Holy Ghoſt, which is a Senſe inconſiſtent with other places of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; or <hi>ſo</hi> as to deny all other things to be God which are not of the ſame Eſſence with the Father: And this Senſe doth exactly well agree with the other parts of Scripture.</q> Thus <hi>Zanchy, loc. ſupr. Citat.</hi> In this laſt Senſe of <hi>Zanchy</hi> doth <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin</hi> determine, That theſe Words of our Saviour are to be taken. Amongſt the various So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſms which are brought by Hereticks againſt the <hi>True</hi> Divinity of the Son of God, <hi>this</hi> he reckons for one of the chiefeſt. And amongſt the general Rules which he gives for anſwering Hereticks, he gives us One particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly for the eaſie anſwering their Argument from thoſe Words of our Saviour, to prove that he is not <hi>the only True God</hi> which he ſays his Father is <hi>vid. Explicat. Catechet. par.</hi> 2. <hi>ſub. Quaeſt.</hi> 33. By his calling the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the only True God, <hi>non excluditur à vera Deitate Filius,</hi> &amp;c. <q>The Son is not excluded from being <hi>the True God,</hi> but Idols and Falſe Deities, to which the Father, the True God is oppos'd.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And a little after, under the ſame Queſtion, having put the Heretical Objection, from thoſe Words of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, for appropriating the Title of the Only True God to the Father, (which is the profeſs'd, great Article of Mr. <hi>J. B</hi>'s Creed) he thus anſwers,</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:44236:35"/>
            <p>
               <q>1ſt.
<note place="margin">1. Ibi fit oppoſitio non Patris, Filii &amp; Spiritus ſancti, fed Dei &amp; Idolorum atque Creaturarum. Particula igitur
<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>ſolum</hi> non excludit à Deitate Filium &amp; Spiritum ſanctum: Sed tantum ea, quibus Pater verus Deus opponitur. 2. Eſt fallacia Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionis. Sequitur enim <hi>&amp; quem miſiſti Jeſum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum.</hi> Ergo in hoc etiam conſiſtit vita aeterna, ut Jeſus Chriſtus à Patre miſſus <hi>ſimiliter</hi> cognoſcatur eſſe <hi>verus Deus,</hi> ſicut dicitur [1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.20.] <hi>Hic eſt verus Deus &amp; vita aeterna.</hi> 3. Eſt criam fallacia Compoſitionis. Nam Excluſiva
<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> non pertinet ad Subjectum <hi>Te,</hi> fed ad Praedicatum <hi>verum Deum.</hi> quod Articulus oſtendit in Graeco,
<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Senſus enim eſt, ut cognoſcant Te Patrem eſſe Deum illum qui ſolus eſt verus Deus. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſm. Explicat. Catechet. Par.</hi> 2. Q. 33. <hi>p.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> There is no Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Father, Son, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt [as if the Father were the only True God and not the Son and the Holy Ghoſt] but the Oppoſition is of the only True God, to Falſe Gods: And therefore the Particle
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>only,</hi> doth not exclude the Son and the Holy Ghoſt, but only thoſe things, to which the Father the True God is oppos'd. 2dly, It is <hi>Fallacia Diviſionis:</hi> For it follows, <hi>and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent:</hi> Therefore in <hi>this</hi> alſo conſiſts Life Eternal, <hi>That</hi> Jeſus Chriſt ſent by the Father, <hi>may in like manner alſo with the Father be acknowledg'd The only True God,</hi> as St. <hi>John</hi> ſays, 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 5.20. [ſpeaking of Chriſt] <hi>This is the True God and Eternal Life.</hi> 3dly, It is a Fallacy of Compoſition. For the excluſive
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>only,</hi> doth not belong to the Subject <hi>Thee</hi> [the Father] but to the Predicate <hi>True God:</hi> And this the Greek Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>ſhews, That they might know Thee <hi>the</hi> only True God. For the Senſe is, That they might know Thee, <hi>the Father,</hi> to be <hi>that God who alone is the True God.</hi>
               </q> Thus <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin,</hi> thus the moſt Learned Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> (who perhaps was as Knowing and as Orthodox a Man as himſelf) will tell him in <hi>Paraph. in Loc.</hi> 
               <q>That if Men will be Partakers of this Eternal Life, <hi>beſide</hi> the Knowledge of the Father, the only True God, they muſt embrace Chriſt and <hi>acknowledge him as the only True God alſo,</hi>
               </q> for which he quotes, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.20. where the ſame beloved Diſciple, who records theſe Words of our Bleſſed Saviour, expreſsly determines (to the Shame and Confuſion of all wicked Hereticks, and idle, ignorant,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:44236:36"/>forward Conſiderers, who muſt needs be making of new Creeds, and appropriate the Title of <hi>One God, only True God to</hi> the Father <hi>Alone</hi>) <hi>That this</hi> [his Son Jeſus Chriſt] <hi>is the True God and Eternal Life;</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>THE</hi> True God. <hi>Hic agitur non ſolum de vero Deo, fed de illo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>no vero Deo, ut Articulus in graeco additus indicat. Catech. Rac.</hi> And ſays the extraordinary Biſhop <hi>Pearſon</hi> upon theſe Words; <q>I can conclude no leſs than that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour is <hi>the True</hi> God, ſo <hi>ſtyl'd</hi> in the Scriptures by way of <hi>Eminency</hi> with an Article prefix'd, as the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Writers which immediately follow'd the Apoſtles, did both ſpeak and write <hi>Expoſ. Creed Art.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 132.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4thly, St. <hi>Hilary,</hi> he ſays, <hi>expreſsly aſſerts this</hi> [the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of only True God] <hi>to be debitum Honorem Patri.</hi> No doubt but St. <hi>Hilary</hi> may. But what's this to his Purpoſe? No Body will deny it to be an Honour due to the Father. But the Queſtion is whether it be an Honour due to the Father <hi>only</hi> or <hi>alone,</hi> excluſively of the Son and the Holy Ghoſt? Let him produce St. <hi>Hilary</hi> ſaying <hi>that,</hi> and then One St. <hi>Hilary</hi> may be allow'd to ſpeak for him. 'Till then we may be ſatisfy'd, that St. <hi>Hilary</hi> Patronizes <hi>this Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priation</hi> no more than, as he ſays, St. <hi>Paul</hi> does; which is,</p>
            <p n="5">5. His 5th. and laſt Argument. St. <hi>Paul,</hi> he ſays, <hi>has Patroniz'd this Appropriation,</hi> Epheſ. 4.6. <hi>To us there is One God and Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What he means by adding [<hi>to us</hi>] to the Text [<hi>There</hi> is One God and Father] I cannot tell, and I do verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he cannot tell himſelf. But this I can tell, and am very ſure of, that this is an Invincible Proof of his more than ordinary ſcandalous ignorance. If his adding [<hi>to us</hi>] ſignifies any thing, it muſt be directly againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. It muſt be to reſtrain the Relation of God's being a Father, to <hi>us his Creatures</hi> or <hi>to us Men</hi> in particular, to <hi>us</hi> his Children by Creation or by Adoption, in Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to or by way of Diſtinction from his Son Chriſt
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:44236:36"/>Jeſus, his Son by Nature, by a ſtrictly proper, true Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. And in truth, in this Senſe is the Term [Father] here moſt certainly to be taken: Not for the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>but</hi> for the Father of all things, of all Men, or of the Elect at leaſt; for ſuch a Father as we invoke in our <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> ſuch a Father as the Son him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and the Holy Ghoſt himſelf is: Not for the Father, the Firſt Perſon of the Ever-Bleſſed Trinity as <hi>diſtinct</hi> from the Second Perſon and the Third, the Son and the Holy Ghoſt; but for the Father who is all Three Perſons, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son and Holy Ghoſt. And let him produce me one Author, if he can, who is accounted Orthodox, who doth not take the Term Father here in <hi>this</hi> Senſe, that is, That the Title here of Father, given by St. <hi>Paul</hi> to God is not Perſonal but Eſſential, <hi>ratione ad extra.</hi> And if ſo (as moſt certainly <hi>ſo</hi> it is) then <hi>this Appropriation</hi> which, he ſays, St. <hi>Paul here</hi> patronizes, it is certain St. <hi>Paul here</hi> doth not patronize, but directly contrary to that which he contends for, and aſſerts, and cites St. <hi>Paul</hi> for, St. <hi>Paul</hi> here gives the Title of <hi>One God</hi> to God the Son and God the Holy Ghoſt, as well as to God the Father, that is, to Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, not taken di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly but conjunctly. And if this Man had but attended a little to common Senſe, and to the Words which imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately follow thoſe which he quotes, he could not but have ſeen this.
<note n="*" place="margin">Dicitur au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tem Pater on nium, quia on nium Creat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Gubernato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt. Tam F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lius autem Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ator eſt &amp; Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritus ſanctus quam Pater ut ante oſtenſum eſt. Et ſic ſaepè apud Prophetas accipitur, ſic etiam ad <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus De &amp; Pater omnium, qui eſt ſuper omnia:</hi> Suo ſcilicet abſoluto &amp; ſummo Imperio. At etiam Fili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuper omnia, <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.31. <hi>Et per omnia:</hi> Sua ſcilicet Univerſali Providentia per omnia diffuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. At etiam Chriſtus omnia agit, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Et in omnibus vobis;</hi> Conjunctione &amp; I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>habitatione, per ſuum Spiritum. Eſt autem in nobis etiam Filius cum Patre: <hi>Jo.</hi> 14.23. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> apparet hoc dictum Apoſtoli ad Solam Patris Perſonam non poſſe Reſtringi. Hi. Zanch. de Tribus E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bim Par.</hi> 2. <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 539.</note> 
               <hi>There is,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Paul, One God and Father
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of All</hi> [of all Things, or of all Men] <hi>who is above All, and through All, and in you All.</hi> Above all by his abſolute, ſupream Power and Dominion: <hi>So</hi> alſo is
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:44236:37"/>the Second Perſon of the Bleſſed Trinity, God the Son, ſaid to be <hi>above All,</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> 3.31. <hi>And through All,</hi> that is, by his univerſal, fatherly Care and good Providence diffus'd through all things: <hi>So</hi> alſo is the Perſon of the Son, who, by this Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 9.5. is ſaid to be <hi>over All, God Bleſſed for ever. Amen.</hi> And <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. that he upholds <hi>All things by his Power. And in you All,</hi> that is, by his gracious Conjunction with us, and Inhabitation in us by his Holy Spirit: So alſo is God the Son <hi>in us</hi> as well as God the Father, as our Bleſſed Lord himſelf tells us, St. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.23. <hi>And Jeſus anſwer'd and ſaid unto him, if a Man love me, he will keep my Words: And my Father will love him, and</hi> WE <hi>will come unto him and make</hi> OUR <hi>abode with him. And thus it appears,</hi> ſays the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Zanchy, That this Saying of the Apoſtle</hi> [there is One God and Father] <hi>cannot be reſtrain'd to the Perſon of the Father alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is not this then an admirable Proof that St. <hi>Paul</hi> patronizes this Appropriation, That the Title of One God is the proper, perſonal Prerogative of the Father alone? That is, That the Firſt Perſon of the Ever-Bleſſed Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Father alone of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>is One God,</hi> becauſe Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are ſo? That is, That the Father <hi>Alone</hi> is ſo, becauſe the Father <hi>alone</hi> is not ſo? 'Tis like Mr. <hi>J. B</hi>'s Way of arguing.</p>
            <p>Now, Sir, I appeal to you (nay, I think I may to all the Orthodox World) whether, if Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> will not be <hi>Orthodox with the Animadverter and</hi> Bellarmin, he may not be <hi>eſteem'd an Heretick [Arian and Macedonian]</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>our Saviour,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> p. 86.</note> St.</hi> Paul, <hi>St.</hi> Hilary, <hi>and all the Orien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Fathers?</hi> Whether ſuch Books as theſe do not <hi>call loud for a</hi> Decretum Oxonienſe, <hi>for a Theological Cenſure from both the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall the Books of <hi>Buchanan,</hi> and <hi>Milton,</hi> and <hi>Goodwin,</hi> and <hi>Baxter,</hi> and <hi>Hunton,</hi> and <hi>Hobbes,</hi> and <hi>Owen,</hi> &amp;c. be
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:44236:37"/>
               <hi>juſtly</hi> cenſur'd and condemn'd to Flames for <hi>Blaſpheming</hi> the King? And ſhall ſuch as theſe eſcape for <hi>Blaſpheming</hi> the great God, the moſt adorable Trinity, and our moſt holy Religion? Shall Men be allowed to dally and play (<hi>Stolida Procacitate,</hi> as <hi>Martial</hi>'s Words are) with the moſt tremendous Myſteries and incomprehenſible Things of Faith? Shall Men be allow'd, with rude and licentious Hands, to break down the ſacred Incloſures of our Faith, that <hi>Hedge of Thorns</hi> (as I remember the Reverend Dean well calls it in his Apology) and endeavour with a kind of Sacrilege, to diſpoſſeſs and rob the Church of thoſe Terms and Diſtinctions ſhe hath been ſo long in Poſſeſſion of, and with which ſhe hath ſo long <hi>ſucceſsfully</hi> defended her Faith <hi>of a Holy Trinity in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in Trinity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have theſe Primitive Terms and Diſtinctions (long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ever the School-men were in Being) been always ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to encounter with, and effectually to baffle and defeat the moſt numerous and moſt ſubtle Hereticks, or no? If not, then, it ſeems, that which we call the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Faith in this Article, hath been all along till now, a baffled, indefenſible Faith. If they have (as moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly they have) why are they not as ſufficient now, as they have been all along? What need have we <hi>of Self-Conſciouſneſs and Mutual Conſciouſneſs, and Three diſtinct, infinite Minds or Spirits?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Reference to the Sacred Articles of Religion</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> [<hi>Book p.</hi> 65.] and it is the beſt thing ſaid in his whole Book, in which I heartily agree with him) <hi>we ought to have a double Care, not only to think but ſpeak inof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſively. To take Care that our Words as well as our Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions be Orthodox; and eſpecially ought we to be thus cautious in the myſterious Articles of the Trinity and Incarnation; where a Word diſorder'd, I had almoſt ſaid a Comma diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plac'd, may render us in the Judgment of the warm, contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Parties, guilty of no leſs than Hereſie. 'Tis St.</hi> Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin<hi>'s
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:44236:38"/>Obſervation concerning the Myſtery of the Trinity, That</hi> nec Periculoſiùs alicubi erratur, nec laborioſiùs aliquid quaeritur. <hi>It is no where more dangerous to err, nor more difficult to apprehend than in this myſterious Subject. A wiſe Perſon will have a great Care to keep the beaten Path, to ſpeak in the receiv'd Language of the Church. The Learned</hi> Calvin <hi>gives us his own Experience,</hi> Expertus pridem ſum, &amp; quidem ſaepiùs, quicun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> de verbis pertinaciùs litigant, fovere occultum virus. <hi>That they who obſtinately quarrel againſt the Phraſes of the Church, are Hereticks in their Hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have no hard Thoughts of the Reverend Dean, God knows my Heart. No Man hath a truer Honour and Veneration for him than my ſelf. I only wiſh he had taken <hi>this double Care, not only to think but to ſpeak inof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſively.</hi> I wiſh he had taken a greater Care <hi>to keep the beaten Path, to ſpeak in the receiv'd Language of the Church;</hi> and then, who can doubt, but that he who hath ſo admirably well acquitted himſelf againſt our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Adverſaries, who hath ſo baffl'd and triumph'd over our diſſenting Adverſaries; and who hath been ſuch a ſevere and juſt Scourge to <hi>Proteſtant Reconcilers, Trimmers and Comprehenſion-Men;</hi> who can doubt but that he would have had the ſame Glory and Succeſs againſt our Socinian Adverſaries?</p>
            <p>But to undertake a Defence of the Catholick Faith, of a Trinity in Unity and Unity in Trinity, by <hi>Self-Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Mutual Conſciouſneſs</hi> (however ingenious it may be, however defenſible it may be) is going a new and unuſual Way to work, or at leaſt with new and unuſual Terms, contrary to a common and good Rule in Divinity, <hi>Novae &amp; Inſolitae Locutiones in Myſteriis Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei non ſunt uſurpandae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to aſſert Three diſtinct, infinite Minds, or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, whatever <hi>Genebrard,</hi> One School-man, may ſay;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:44236:38"/>as Learned and a more Orthodox Man than he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <q>
                  <hi>Certè</hi> Pernicioſum <hi>Dogma eſt Tres conſtituere Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus aeternos &amp; diſtinctos. Nam</hi> Januam <hi>aperit non ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ad Arianiſmum, ſed</hi> Palam Gentiliſmum <hi>ſapit.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>Benedict. Aretius Loc. Theolog. Loc.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 4. It is certainly, ſays he, a <hi>Pernicious</hi> Doctrine to conſtitute Three eternal, diſtinct Spirits: For it not only opens a Door to <hi>Arianiſm,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vitandi ſunt omnes modi loquendi, qui Haereticis vel in <hi>Speciem</hi> favere videntur. Qui igitur de Tribus Perſonis adorandae Trinitatis lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur, ii uti non debent ſupradicto loquendi modo, dicentes eas eſſe Tres Subſtantias, ne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere videantur <hi>Arianis, Macedonianis, Valentino Gentili,</hi> &amp; ejus Sectatoribus. <hi>Rob. Baronii Philof. Theol. Ancillans, Exercitat.</hi> 1. <hi>Artic.</hi> 9. <hi>p.</hi> 41.</note> but it <hi>plainly</hi> reliſhes of <hi>Heatheniſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reverend Dean himſelf, as well as Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding what his <hi>Genebrard</hi> ſays) allows it to be <hi>new and unuſual,</hi> and therefore, be ſure, to aſſert it and inſiſt upon it, is not, as Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> gravely adviſes, it is not to have a <hi>great</hi> Care to keep the beaten Path, to ſpeak in the <hi>receiv'd</hi> Language of the Church, which, he ſays, <hi>a wiſe Perſon will do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Reverend Dean means no more by Three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, infinite Minds or Spirits, than Three diſtinct, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Perſons, why ſhould he alter the conſtant, univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Language of the Church? Why ſhould he not be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with aſſerting a Trinity only of Three Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which in an ineffable, incomprehenſible Manner, are One infinite Spirit or God? Why ſhould Occaſion be given to the Enemies of the Tri-Une God, and our moſt Holy Religion to blaſpheme? Cannot a Trinity of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons in One infinite undivided Eſſence be defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unleſs we aſſert Three diſtinct, infinite Minds or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits? How hath it been defended all along hitherto?</p>
            <p>But this is not the worſt of it. That which I chiefly mean, that which calls loudeſt for a <hi>Decretum Oxonienſe,</hi> for a Theological Cenſure from both the Univerſities, is the foul, pernicious Spirit of Latitudinarianiſm, which
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:44236:39"/>being transform'd, by an infernal Artifice, appears much abroad like an Angel of Light, like the only Complaiſant, Sober, Moderate, Peaceable, Healing Angel. But Sheep's Clothing is ſuch a common Diſguiſe, and worn ſo very thin, that we can eaſily look through it and ſee the raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wolf under. If the falſe Prophets will be playing their juggling Tricks, we need not be deceiv'd by them, unleſs we will our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Our Bleſſed Saviour, who would have us enter in at the <hi>ſtrait</hi> Gate,
<note place="margin">Matt. 7.13, 15, 16.</note> and to go the <hi>narrow</hi> Way which leadeth unto Life, and to avoid, as we would Death, the <hi>wide</hi> Gate and the <hi>Latitudinarian</hi> Way, which, he ſaith, <hi>lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to Deſtruction;</hi> hath commanded us to <hi>beware of falſe Prophets,</hi> and that we may know them, he hath given us a certain, infallible Direction <hi>by their Fruits,</hi> that is, as the Word [Fruits] is certainly here to be underſtood, by their Deſigns and Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Behold then <hi>the working of the Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the vehement, the ſubtle, the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand working of the Myſtery of Iniquity.</p>
            <p>After a long (but bleſſed be God hitherto vain and fruitleſs) Attack upon our Out-works and incomparable Liturgy, we find at laſt Men at work to <hi>Sap</hi> the very Foundation of our Church, to undermine and ſubvert the Fundamental Doctrine <hi>of a Trinity of Divine Perſons in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Divine Eſſence,</hi> and ſo to pull down not only the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but the Holy Catholick Church all at once.</p>
            <p>It muſt be dangerous to charge my good Lord Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi> with having any Hand in this, becauſe he is a Peer of the Realm, and therefore <hi>I here Declare</hi> I do not.</p>
            <p>But I hope I may be permitted to ask a civil Queſtion or Two without Offence, though ſome may think I look aſquint upon my Lord.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:44236:39"/>
            <p>What can any Man mean, in a State of this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy, to call the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt Three Perſons, <hi>as the Opinion of a Third Party of Men;</hi> but when he comes to ſpeak of <hi>them</hi> himſelf, to call 'em <hi>the Bleſſed Three,</hi> and to aſſign 'em only ſuch a general Diſtinction, as, for what I know, will agree to the Hypotheſis of any Heretick whatſoever, that ever yet appear'd againſt a Trinity of Divine Perſons, as believ'd by the Holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church? What Sabellian, Arian, Macedonian, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian, Anti-Trinitarian of any Sort, will ſtick to call the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt the Bleſſed Three? Some will have them to be the Bleſſed Three, but not Three diſtinct Perſons, but only Three Names for One and the ſame God. Some will have 'em to be the Bleſſed Three, but not One and the ſame God. And others will have 'em to be Three diſtinct Gods. However ſuch Men as theſe tell us what they mean, and what they would have.</p>
            <p>But what can that Man mean, who though he may now and then for Faſhion's Sake (that is, for the Sake of Trimming) call 'em Three Perſons, yet in a Catechetical, Deciſive Diſcourſe to the Clergy, ſhall plainly affect to call 'em <hi>the Bleſſed Three?</hi> Why not the Three Bleſſed Perſons, according to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Language and Faith of the Church?
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>The Reaſon which the Animadverter, on Mr.</hi> Hill<hi>'s Book, gives why the Biſhop of</hi> Sarum, <hi>in a late Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of his, doth not every where make uſe of the Word</hi> Perſon, <hi>which is conſecrated by ſo long a Cuſtom in the Church; and why he does more frequently ſay the Bleſſed Three, is, becauſe they are not call'd Perſons in Scripture, and the Arians and Socinians look upon it as Foreign, and which, the Foreign Doctor himſelf ſays, needs to be ſoftned to give it a Senſe free from Abſurdity in the Matter of the Trinity, and that it ſerves</hi> only <hi>to render the Diſpute intricate.</hi> Vid. <hi>Animadverſions on Mr.</hi> Hill<hi>'s Book,</hi> p. 4, 5.</note> Why <q>That, my Reverend Brethren, (may ſuch a Man ſay) is a doubtful, diſputed Caſe. Call 'em only the Bleſſed Three, and then you are ſure; then you ſpeak the true Latitudinarian Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; then you are ſure, that is, to be on the ſunny Side of the Hedge; then you are ſure to offend none of the <hi>Three Parties</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>[But that, ſay I, is a Miſtake, my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:44236:40"/>Brethren, For</hi> though it may be no <hi>Offence to the Jews nor to the Gentiles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor 10.32.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Yet a very grievous Offence, I am very ſure, it is to the Church of God, to allow Men a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty (as the Caſe of the Church now ſtands) to expreſs their Faith in the Trinity at this looſe Rate; to ſtyle the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt the Bleſſed Three: For that may ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie Three mere Modes, or Three Names only, Three Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whats, e'en what Men pleaſe</hi>] the Ancient Fathers, indeed, <q>were pleaſed univerſally to call 'em the Three Bleſſed Perſons, or ſomething equivalent to the calling them Three Perſons, which inferr'd a <hi>Real Perſonal Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> But they, too many of them and the Moderns too, in their Defence of the Holy Catholick Faith againſt thoſe they call'd Hereticks, have perhaps gone beyond due Bounds; nay, it may be juſtly queſtioned, whether [by what they have deliver'd down to us concerning this Myſtery] they have made it better to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood or more firmly believ'd, or whether others have not taken Advantage to repreſent theſe Subtilties as Dregs either of <hi>Aeones,</hi> of the <hi>Valentinians,</hi> or of the Platonick Notions. And it being long before theſe Theories were well ſtated and ſettled, it is no Wonder if many of the Fathers have not only differ'd from One another, but even from themſelves in ſpeaking upon this Argument. When Men go about to explain a thing, of which they can have no diſtinct Idea; it is very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural for them to run out into <hi>vauſt</hi> Multiplicity of Words; into great Length and much Darkneſs and Confuſion. Many impertinent Similes will be urg'd, and often impertinent Reaſonings will be made uſe of, all which are the unavoidable Conſequences of a Man's going about to explain to others what he does not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly underſtand himſelf. And ſo the Fathers are to be caſhier'd, not to be regarded in this Matter. What Matter is it what a parcel of old, doating, Doctors ſay,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:44236:40"/>
                  <hi>who have gone beyond due Bounds, contradicted each other, and themſelves, who uſe many impertinent Similes, run out into a vauſt Length and Confuſion, while they talk of things to others which they underſtand not themſelves.</hi> Beſides too theſe Fathers were no Latitudinarians. They were a Sort of ſtrait-lac'd, ſtiff, old, Gentlemen, who hated what we call Trimming mortally; and could never be perſwaded for the Sake of Comprehenſion, to ſacrifice any part of the Doctrine or Diſcipline of the Church to the Caprice of Sabellians or Arians, Novatians or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts, or any Hereticks or Schiſmaticks whatſoever.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Very agreeably to this, out came Animadverſions on Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s Book, Intituled, A Vindication of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Fathers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In a Letter to a Perſon of Quality: Which Perſon of Quality, as a French Divine in our Neighbourhood reports, is my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Sarum,</hi> who order'd it to be Tranſlated out of its Original French into Engliſh, and to be Printed.</p>
            <p>In which Letter theſe <hi>Ignorant, Impertinent, Self-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting Old Fathers,</hi> without any Reverence or Regard to their Venerable Grey Hairs, are run down and troden under Foot moſt wofully: And the Author of it, like a good, humble, fawning Creature very devoutly Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices the Primitive Fathers to his Maker the Biſhop, and very impiouſly gives them up to the Hereticks.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Bull, he ſays [<hi>Animadverſ. p.</hi> 32.] <hi>and ſome Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Men indeed, have endeavour'd to give a good Senſe to their Expreſſions, and by a long Compaſs of Conſequences to reduce them to the Ordinary Notions.</hi> But it will not do. <hi>Notwithſtanding all Dr.</hi> Bull<hi>'s Endeavours to reduce what the Fathers ſay</hi> [concerning the Trinity] <hi>to an Orthodox Senſe,</hi> p. 52. They were certainly Hereticks, as bad Hereticks as thoſe they oppos'd, for all that. For, ſays this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane <hi>Patrum-Maſtix,</hi> p. 51. <hi>Moſt of the Fathers from the middle of the Second Century to the Council of</hi> Nice, <hi>were
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:44236:41"/>engag'd in Opinions <hi>contrary to the right Notion</hi> we have of the Doctrine of the Trinity, as</hi> Petavius <hi>confeſſes it.</hi> And therefore <hi>'tis one thing to be miſh'd,</hi> he ſays in the ſame Page, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Hill <hi>had not inſpir'd his Readers with ſo profound a Veneration for Antiquity;</hi> which I am ſure our Holy Mother the Church of <hi>England</hi> ever had, and hath, (and 'tis her Glory) and juſtly obliges all her Children, her Miniſters eſpecially, to have.
<note n="*" place="margin">Imprimis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro videbunt, ne quid unquam doceant pro concione, quod à Populo religiosè teneri &amp; credi velint, niſi quod conſentaneum ſit Doctrinae veteris aut novi Teſtamenti, quodque ex illa ipſa Doctrina Catholici Patres &amp; veteres Epiſcopi collegerint. Qui ſecus fecerit, &amp; contraria Doctrina Populum turbaverit, excommunicabitur. Liber quorundam Canonum Diſcip. Ec. <hi>Ang.</hi> An. 1571. Sub Tit. Concionatores. <hi>I take it for granted that this Canon extends to Books as well as Sermons, and then quaere whether, according to this excellent Canon of our Church, Mr.</hi> Hill <hi>cannot juſtify what he ſays in</hi> p. 6, 7. <hi>of his Book, for which this Animadverter fanatically charges him with Popery? And whether, according to the ſame Canon, this Animadverting Foreigner (advanced as it were for a Purpoſe) ought not to be Animadverted upon, and to be made a Foreigner in a worſe Senſe than he was before; that is, to be Excommunicated out of our Church.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed in what this Animadverter here ſays, he ſpeaks ſomewhat ſlily, and his Words may poſſibly be taken in <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Favoris,</hi> Hypothetically only: But what he ſays before, precludes ſuch an Interpretation and forbids the Favour. For in <hi>that</hi> he is Categorical, That ſeveral of the Ancient Fathers were Tritheiſts, and the reverend Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s a Tritheiſt too. That's out of doubt with him. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſays he, <hi>p.</hi> 41. <hi>I agree with him</hi> [Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>] <hi>when he tells us, that he cannot conceive Three Minds in God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eſtabliſhing Tritheiſm. But,</hi> ſays he, <hi>he</hi> [Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>] <hi>is abſolutely miſtaken, when he denies that ſeveral of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients have acknowledged Three Minds in God.</hi> And if to be Three Minds is to be Three Subſtances, that's as clear too as the Day, that the Fathers own'd Three Subſtances in God. <hi>Nothing,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is more evident than that MOST of the Fathers have acknowledged Three Subſtances. This,</hi> he ſays, <hi>he can ſoon demonſtrate, if he will,</hi> that is, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, if the Biſhop will have him. And if Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> or any Body elſe ſhall dare to ſpeak a Word againſt his Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:44236:41"/>for the future, for reflecting upon, or ſaying what he pleaſes of the Ancient Fathers, the Monſieur, who, he ſays, is <hi>almoſt tempted</hi> to do it already, will then, no doubt, be able to hold no longer, from <hi>Drawing ſuch a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Antiquity</hi> [with Relation to its Faith in the Holy Trinity] <hi>as <hi>ſhall not be much to its Advantage,</hi> p.</hi> 31.</p>
            <p>This is certainly a very Formidable, Dangerous Man, and I hope it will be a Warning to Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> and all others to take Care, <hi>for the Sake of the Ancient Fathers,</hi> how they provoke him or his Biſhop.</p>
            <p>But our Prefacer here, Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> advances yet further in this Work of Darkneſs, and under a falſe Pretence of defending the Catholick Doctrine of the Bleſſed Trinity againſt the Objections of the Socinians, and of defending the Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s (by a Book which, I dare ſay, that truly Worthy, and deſervedly Admir'd Perſon, did neither encourage nor approve of) doth not only publiſh ſuch a Profeſſion of his Faith, as, I am ſure, there is not a Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian in <hi>England,</hi> but what will readily own and ſubſcribe to; but with unparallell'd Ignorance, or <hi>ſomething worſe,</hi> brings the Nicene Council, <hi>All</hi> the Oriental Fathers, St. <hi>Hilary,</hi> our Bleſſed Saviour, and his Bleſſed Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> to vouch it; that is, That the Father <hi>Alone is the One only True God, the God whom the Heathen Philoſophers by the Light of Nature, and the Jews by Revelation wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, who, he believes was One Divine Perſon,</hi> and <hi>but</hi> One Divine Perſon. For he doth, he ſays, <hi>moſt firmly believe the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of God AS it was believ'd by the wiſeſt of the Heathens,</hi> and the Jewiſh Church, who, ſure enough, believ'd the One God to be but One Divine Perſon: And therefore, though there be Gods many and Lords many [falſly ſo call'd] and though Chriſt may be call'd God, and the Holy Ghoſt God [that can be only metaphori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, for] to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> [Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> and his Co-Believers] there is but <hi>One only True God, the Father Alone.</hi> And,</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:44236:42"/>
            <p>This is the Bottom upon which his ſuitable Doctrine, here in his Preface, ſtands, <hi>viz. That the Firſt Perſon of the Bleſſed Trinity, the Father is adequately and convertibly predicated of God, but the Three Perſons, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are not;</hi> that is (and All the Earth, I am ſure, cannot make any thing elſe of it) the One True God is the Father <hi>alone,</hi> but the One True God (according to the Catholick Faith) is not Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt. <hi>The Scriptures prove the former, and 'tis downright Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to deny it: And the Scriptures confute the latter,</hi> and 'tis downright Blaſphemy (as he undertakes to prove it) to aſſert it.</p>
            <p>This, I think, appears plainly to be his Faith as he hath deliver'd it, and which he decretorily eſtabliſhes with a kind of Anathema. And,</p>
            <p>If <hi>This</hi> be his Faith, if <hi>This</hi> be his Doctrine, can the Univerſities, or can the Governours of our Church be unconcern'd to ſtigmatize ſuch a Believer, and to condemn by publick Cenſure, ſuch Doctrine as this is, from a Man that writes himſelf A. M. and Presbyter of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> Can we be leſs concern'd <hi>to render to God the things that are God's, than to render to Caeſar the things that are Caeſar's?</hi> I hope not.</p>
            <p>Certainly, however ſuch Authors as this may eſcape for ſome time, there <hi>will</hi> come a Day of Reckoning for them here as well as hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Buchanan</hi> and <hi>Knox,</hi> and <hi>Goodman,</hi> and <hi>Parſons,</hi> &amp;c. were gone long before; but yet a <hi>Decretum Oxonienſe</hi> at laſt overtook them, and juſtly condemned their Books to lie in Infamous Aſhes with their Authors.</p>
            <p>And now, Sir, to conclude this great Trouble I have given you. I know you utterly diſlike all harſh, tart, calumnious Language in the Management of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of Religion: But I know too, That no Man is more for taking down Pride and Inſolence than your ſelf, and for
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:44236:42"/>taking the wiſe Man's Direction, upon ſo juſt an Occaſion as this certainly is, to anſwer <hi>a Man</hi> according to his <hi>Way,</hi> leſt he be wiſe in his own Conceit
<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 26.9.</note>. And this Rule, I hope, I have not tranſgreſs'd, and that it will therefore, with my God, with you and with all the equal and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial, be my Apology for my Way of Writing.</p>
            <p>I do, Sir, heartily wiſh with you that the Acute and Learned Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> in his Vindication of the Primitive Fathers (which, God knows, they never wanted more) had treated the Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi> with more Regard to his great Character, and had better conſider'd that <hi>Michael</hi> the Arch-Angel, when contending with the Devil, he diſputed about the Body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> durſt not bring againſt him a railing Accuſation, but ſaid, The Lord rebuke thee
<note n="†" place="margin">Jude 9.</note>. And more heartily do I wiſh, with you, That the unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionably Ingenious, and Learned Animadverter, if he muſt be exerciſing his Satyr, had kept it all for <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> all Regicides, Rebels, Fanaticks, and the like Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, (upon whom he hath beſtow'd it plentifully and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps plauſibly enough) and had treated the Reverend Dean more humanely and chriſtianly, with a more due Regard to his Former, Meritorious Services for our Church and Religion; and to that Character, which he deſervedly hath in the Church, and I hope will have a greater. And if the Animadverter had done ſo, I am apt to think that his Arguments againſt the Dean had gone a great deal further, and that therefore he may take his ill Language the better and thank him for't.</p>
            <p>But now, as for this Mr. <hi>J. B. what muſt we ſay,</hi> to uſe his own Words [<hi>Book p.</hi> 133.] <hi>when a Perſon ſhall ſet up for a Critick in the moſt myſterious Article of our Religion, and himſelf underſtands not the Firſt Elements of Divinity?</hi> When <hi>ſuch</hi> a Perſon ſhall undertake, after an inſolent Manner, to Chaſtize the Animadverter, and through his whole Preface and Book, ſhall be perpetually inſulting
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:44236:43"/>over and vilifying <hi>a Man</hi> for underſtanding nothing of Logick or Divinity, who, let him be what he will elſe, hath been a long while celebrated for a zealous, always ſtedfaſt Son of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and for a Man of great Parts and Learning, which he, I'll engage, never will? When ſuch a Perſon ſhall be ſo unſufferably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited and vain, as to think himſelf not only an Over-Match for the Animadverter, but for St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> the Maſter of the Sentences, and all the School-men and Moderns who are their Followers? Who after he hath ſingl'd out <hi>the Acute and Learned</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> as he calls him, <hi>p.</hi> 58. for a confuted, baffled Man by him, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed him and mock'd him, as a bold, ignorant, ſhuffling Father, and run down, deſpis'd, and ridicul'd the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties of the Schools, which, 'tis certain, he hath not Brains to underſtand, though others have; ſhall expoſe and ridicule the Holy Scriptures themſelves, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly pervert them to Senſes, which, 'tis certain were never intended by them; and ſhall undertake to publiſh ſuch a Profeſſion of his Faith as is utterly inconſiſtent with the Catholick, and under a Pretence of defending the Trinity, ſhall ignorantly or treacherouſly betray it, and as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſays, ſhall privily bring in damnable He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, even denying the Lord that bought him, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>What ſhall we ſay?</hi> Shall ſuch a Perſon be complemented? Was ſoft Language ever created for ſuch a Man? Who then can deſerve to be rebuk'd <hi>ſharply? Tit.</hi> 1.3.</p>
            <p>I do not, I am ſure I cannot, expoſe and chaſtize him as he deſerves, or as the Reverend Dean did the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciler in his Excellent <hi>Vindication of the Rights of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Authority;</hi> and therefore I hope, I ſhall not fall under your Diſpleaſure for borrowing this Man's hard Words, and applying them upon Occaſion, more ſuitably to himſelf, and juſtly laſhing him [my Equal] with his own Rod (with which he ſo irreverently and unjuſtly preſumes to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:44236:43"/>correct, in all Reſpects, his Superiour) in <hi>Vindication of the Rights of Heaven,</hi> of the Holy and Eternal Jeſus, and the Ever-Bleſſed Spirit of God, who with the Father, according to the Catholick Faith, <hi>are adequately and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertibly predicated of the One True God,</hi> which he, <hi>in Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis,</hi> blaſphemouſly denies, and impiouſly ſays that the <hi>Scriptures confute.</hi> I am, Sir, moſt ſincerely,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your very Affectionate, very Humble Servant,</hi>
T. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:44236:44"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A POSTSCRIPT to the</hi> READER.</head>
            <p>I Had written a great Part of this Letter to my reverend Friend Mr. <hi>R.E.</hi> without any the leaſt Thoughts, God knows, of making it publick. But upon a Serious Poſt-Conſideration, that it may be a means (which I am ſure, will be a good Piece of Service to our Church and Religion) to divert Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> from any further Proſecution of a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, which, I think, I have fully prov'd and ſatisfy'd you (and, I hope, Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> himſelf) he is altogether unfit and unqualify'd for; and to oblige him <hi>for Shame</hi> not to think of Publiſhing his <hi>Threaten'd</hi> Second Part <hi>of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of God,</hi> or at leaſt to be more cautious in it, that the Church may not be ſcandaliz'd and peſter'd with any more of <hi>his Haſty Births; I Reſolv'd</hi> to let it go abroad with <hi>This Proteſtation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That I have no manner of Knowledge of this Mr. <hi>J.B.</hi> but by his Book. That therefore what I have ſaid of or againſt him, is not out of any perſonal Pique, Grudge, or Ill-will I bear him, but (what I beg the candid Reader in his Chriſtian Charity to me to believe) <hi>purely</hi> out of an honeſt, ſincere Zeal for the Glory of the Holy and Eternal Trinity, <hi>AS</hi> 'tis reveal'd to us in the Holy Bible, according to the conſtant Senſe and Interpretation of the Holy Catholick Church, from the Holy Apoſtles Days to our own: And particularly of our Holy Mother the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the Firſt Article of her Religion, and in her incomparable Liturgy; which I beſeech God of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Mercy, to preſerve intire to us from <hi>All</hi> clande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine Deſigns and Practices, and <hi>All</hi> open Aſſaults and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olations of <hi>All</hi> fickle, new-fangled Teachers and Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers: To which, I am ſure, every true, zealous, ſtedfaſt Son of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> will moſt heartily and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly ſay with me, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:44236:44"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
